<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/</link><description>Recent content in Projects on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>130 Years of Swiss Parliament</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/130-years-swiss-parliament/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/130-years-swiss-parliament/</guid><description>We are currently working on two funded research projects surrounding the Swiss Parliament. The first project is a collaboration with the Swiss Data Science Center to build a searchable database of the Swiss Parliament. The second project is an SNF-funded project that examines how members of parliament have shaped the Swiss political landscape throughout the past 130 years.
Check back here regularly, for updates on the projects, insights into how we extract the data and our most recent findings.</description></item><item><title>Data Science</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/data-science/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/data-science/</guid><description>In our research, we address various issues pertaining to the broader topic of data science. We are particularly interested in the development of methods for the study of large relational datasets, complex systems analysis, and collections of time-stamped interactions from various disciplines.
The methods highlighted here range from network science tools, data scraping and inference, and disambiguation.</description></item><item><title>Network Theory</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/network-theory/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/network-theory/</guid><description>Networks provide an optimal representation for complex systems. As different systems and different scientific questions require different approaches to be answered, we constantly develop network based methods to suit our needs.
Check back here regularly, for updates on the project, insights into how we extract the data and our most recent findings.</description></item><item><title>Resilience</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/resilience/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/resilience/</guid><description>The study of the resilience of complex systems is one of the projects at the core of our group. Our works span theoretical investigations about how to define, quantify, and study resilience, and applied analysis of real world systems. We are particularly interested in the study of social organisations ranging from Online Software Developers communities, to large collaboration networks of firms.
Check back here regularly, for updates on the project, insights into how we extract the data and our most recent findings.</description></item></channel></rss>