<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/</link><description>Recent content in Projects on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 17:36:19 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pharmaceutical Supply Chain Resilience</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/pharmaceutical-supply-chain-resilience/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/pharmaceutical-supply-chain-resilience/</guid><description>Overview Welcome to our research hub on pharmaceutical supply chain resilience. Our work addresses the critical issue of drug shortages, driven by complex logistical, economic, and geopolitical challenges that impact the availability of essential medicines.
Research Focus We explore pharmaceutical supply chain resilience, complex economic systems, and the broader economic aspects of the pharmaceutical sector. Our aim is to enhance the reliability of pharmaceutical distribution, ensuring medicines remain accessible during disruptions.</description></item><item><title>Signed Relations and Structural Balance in Complex Systems: From Data to Models</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/signed-relations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/signed-relations/</guid><description>According to the theory of structural balance, interacting systems balance the (positive or negative) relations between different system elements such that local conflicts are minimized. Hence, structural imbalances induce a dynamics to resolve such conflicts. This dynamics plays a vital role in evolutionary processes because a multitude of possible solutions exists. At the same time, if these solutions cannot be reached, this can hamper the functionality of systems. This general problem also occurs in social systems, where instead of a more balanced state, for instance, the polarization of opinions emerges.</description></item><item><title>Resilience</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/resilience/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/resilience/</guid><description>Resilience denotes the capacity of a system to withstand shocks and the ability to recover from them. Hence, it combines two different concepts: Robustness captures the structural and adaptivity the dynamic dimension of resilience.
Conversely, resilience cannot be reduced to notions of robustness or stability. Rigid systems in engineering or society can be quite robust against shocks, but once they fail, they never recover. Resilience addresses the recovery, i.e. the response after shock.</description></item><item><title>How software teams (self-)organise</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/software-engineering/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/software-engineering/</guid><description>Software has become an integral part of our daily lives. We are woken up by the alarm app on our phones; we use navigation software to commute to work; we use social media to interact with friends and collaborators around the world. Software is created by diverse teams where different developers have different backgrounds, specialisations, and experiences. Managing such teams is a challenging task that needs to account for this diversity while delivering timely and robust code.</description></item><item><title>Systems interventions</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/systems/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 18:33:20 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/systems/</guid><description>Systems design denotes an approach to manipulate technical, environmental, social or economic systems such that a desired outcome is obtained. This can be achieved in a bottom-up or a top-down manner or a combination of both.
In our models, we use different approaches, such as network controllability and network interventions, nudging and mechanism design. Our publications demonstrate: It works!</description></item><item><title>130 Years of Swiss Parliament</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/130-years-of-swiss-parliament/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/130-years-of-swiss-parliament/</guid><description>We are currently working on two funded research projects surrounding the Swiss Parliament. The first project is a collaboration with the Swiss Data Science Center to build a searchable database of the Swiss Parliament. The second project is an SNF-funded project that examines how members of parliament have shaped the Swiss political landscape throughout the past 130 years.
Check back here regularly, for updates on the projects, insights into how we extract the data and our most recent findings.</description></item><item><title>Economic networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/economic-networks/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/economic-networks/</guid><description>Economic networks are one of our main research topics, for more than 15 years. We have developed a broad range of methods for reconstructing such networks from data (finance, credit, risk), novel measures for quantifying network relations (control, ownership, exposure) and agent based and network models for the dynamics of these networks.
Checkout the respective projects for more details.
financial networks
ownership networks
R&amp;amp;D collaboration networks
trade networks</description></item><item><title>R&amp;D collaboration network of firms</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/rd-collaborations/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 20:06:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/rd-collaborations/</guid><description>Research and Development (R&amp;amp;D) networks among firms are a prime example of large-scale economic networks. Firms collaborate bilaterally or in small groups to exchange knowledge, this way increasing their knowledge stock. Because most firms are engaged in several collaborations at the same time, a large network emerges. It evolves over time, because firms can leave the network if their costs exceed their benefits, new firms can enter, collaborations are terminated and new collaborations are established.</description></item><item><title>Data Science</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/data-science/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/data-science/</guid><description>In our research, we address various issues pertaining to the broader topic of data science. We are particularly interested in the development of methods for the study of large relational datasets, complex systems analysis, and collections of time-stamped interactions from various disciplines.
The methods highlighted here range from network science tools, data scraping and inference, and disambiguation.</description></item><item><title>Science of Science</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/science-of-science/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/science-of-science/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Network Theory</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/network-theory/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/network-theory/</guid><description>Networks provide an optimal representation for complex systems. As different systems and different scientific questions require different approaches to be answered, we constantly develop network based methods to suit our needs.
Check back here regularly, for updates on the project, insights into how we extract the data and our most recent findings.</description></item><item><title>Social relations</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/social-relations/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/social-relations/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Economic Geography</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/economic-geography/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/economic-geography/</guid><description>Economic geography analyses and models the spatial distribution of economic activities. Examples include the location of firms in cities, the worldwide R&amp;amp;D collaborations of firms, the concentration of foreign direct investments in particular regions, or the competition of production centers.</description></item></channel></rss>