<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Complex Network Approach to Data Science on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/</link><description>Recent content in The Complex Network Approach to Data Science on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Disentangling homophily, community structure and triadic closure in networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/peixoto/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/peixoto/</guid><description>Abstract One of the most typical properties of network data is the presence of homophily, i.e. the increased tendency of an edge to exist between two nodes if they share the same underlying characteristic, such as a social parameter, metabolic role, etc. More broadly, when the underlying similarity parameter is not specified a priori, the same homophily pattern is known as community structure. Another pervasive pattern encountered in the same kinds of networks is transitivity, i.</description></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/cbreak/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/cbreak/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data Science on Knowledge Graphs: from Complex Data to Network Models</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/casiraghi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/casiraghi/</guid><description>Abstract One of the most typical properties of network data is the presence of homophily, i.e. the increased tendency of an edge to exist between two nodes if they share the same underlying characteristic, such as a social parameter, metabolic role, etc. More broadly, when the underlying similarity parameter is not specified a priori, the same homophily pattern is known as community structure. Another pervasive pattern encountered in the same kinds of networks is transitivity, i.</description></item><item><title>De Bruijn Goes Neural: Towards Causality-Aware Graph Neural Networks for Time Series Data</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/scholtes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/scholtes/</guid><description>Abstract Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) have become a cornerstone for the application of deep learning to data on complex networks, i.e. relational data that capture interactions between nodes. However, we increasingly have access to time-resolved data that not only capture which nodes are connected to each other, but also when and in which temporal order those connections occur. A number of works have shown how the timing and ordering of links shapes the causal topology of networked systems, i.</description></item></channel></rss>