<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Complex Network Approach to Data Science on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/</link><description>Recent content in The Complex Network Approach to Data Science on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Disentangling homophily, community structure and triadic closure in networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/peixoto/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/peixoto/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>One of the most typical properties of network data is the presence of homophily, i.e. the increased tendency of an edge to exist between two nodes if they share the same underlying characteristic, such as a social parameter, metabolic role, etc. More broadly, when the underlying similarity parameter is not specified a priori, the same homophily pattern is known as community structure. Another pervasive pattern encountered in the same kinds of networks is transitivity, i.e. the increased tendency of observing an edge between two nodes if they share a neighbor in common. Although these patterns are indicative of two distinct mechanisms of network formation, namely choice or constraint homophily and triadic closure, respectively, they are generically conflated in non-longitudinal data. This is because both processes can result in the same kinds of observation: 1. the preferred connection between nodes of the same kind can induce the presence of triangles involving similar nodes, and 2. the tendency of triangles to be formed can induce the formation of groups of nodes with a higher density of connections between them, when compared to the rest of the network. This conflation means we cannot reliably interpret the underlying mechanisms of network formation merely from the abundance of triangles or observed community structure in network data.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/cbreak/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/cbreak/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data Science on Knowledge Graphs: from Complex Data to Network Models</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/casiraghi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/casiraghi/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>One of the most typical properties of network data is the presence of homophily, i.e. the increased tendency of an edge to exist between two nodes if they share the same underlying characteristic, such as a social parameter, metabolic role, etc. More broadly, when the underlying similarity parameter is not specified a priori, the same homophily pattern is known as community structure. Another pervasive pattern encountered in the same kinds of networks is transitivity, i.e. the increased tendency of observing an edge between two nodes if they share a neighbor in common. Although these patterns are indicative of two distinct mechanisms of network formation, namely choice or constraint homophily and triadic closure, respectively, they are generically conflated in non-longitudinal data. This is because both processes can result in the same kinds of observation: 1. the preferred connection between nodes of the same kind can induce the presence of triangles involving similar nodes, and 2. the tendency of triangles to be formed can induce the formation of groups of nodes with a higher density of connections between them, when compared to the rest of the network. This conflation means we cannot reliably interpret the underlying mechanisms of network formation merely from the abundance of triangles or observed community structure in network data.
In this talk I present a solution to this problem, consisting in a principled method to disentangle homophily and community structure from triadic closure in network data. This is achieved by formulating a generative model that includes community structure in a first instance, and an iterated process of triadic closure in a second. Based on this model, we develop a Bayesian inference algorithm that is capable of identifying which edges are more likely to be due to community structure or triadic closure, in addition to the underlying community structure itself. As I show, this reconstruction yields a detailed interpretation of the underlying mechanisms of network formation, allowing us to identify macro-scale structures that emerge spontaneously from micro-scale higher-order interactions, and in this way we can separate them from inherently macro-scale structures. I show how the method can evade the detection of spurious communities caused solely by the formation of triangles in the network, and how it can improve the performance of link prediction when compared to the pure version of the model without triadic closure.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>De Bruijn Goes Neural: Towards Causality-Aware Graph Neural Networks for Time Series Data</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/scholtes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2022_cn/scholtes/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) have become a cornerstone for the application of deep learning to data on complex networks, i.e. relational data that capture interactions between nodes. However, we increasingly have access to time-resolved data that not only capture which nodes are connected to each other, but also when and in which temporal order those connections occur. A number of works have shown how the timing and ordering of links shapes the causal topology of networked systems, i.e. which nodes can possibly influence each other over time. Moreover, higher-order network models have been developed that allow us to model patterns in the resulting causal topology. While those works have shed light on the question how the time dimension of dynamic graphs influences node centralities, community structures, or the evolution of dynamical processes, we lack methods to incorporate those insights into state-of-the-art deep graph learning techniques.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>