<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pharmaceutical Supply Chain Resilience on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/pharmaceutical-supply-chain-resilience/</link><description>Recent content in Pharmaceutical Supply Chain Resilience on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/pharmaceutical-supply-chain-resilience/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Podcast on Drug Shortage Mitigation</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/2024_10_podcast/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 17:36:19 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/2024_10_podcast/</guid><description>&amp;#9658; 0:00 / 0:00 1 1.25 1.5 Your browser does not support the audio element. To make [our research on drug shortage mitigation and prevention](/projects/pharmaceutical-supply-chain-resilience/) accessible to a broader audience, we created an AI-generated podcast. The podcast discusses our findings on pharmaceutical supply chain resilience (see the [project page](/projects/pharmaceutical-supply-chain-resilience/) for a list of publications). Additionally, the podcast provides a broad overview of our current research focus: developing a shortage mitigation system for pharmaceutical supply chains called ARIADNE.</description></item><item><title>Efficiency and resilience: Key drivers of distribution network growth</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/publications/2024/amico2024efficiency-and-resilience/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/publications/2024/amico2024efficiency-and-resilience/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Tracing Opioids Across the US: A High-Resolution Pharmaceutical Distribution Dataset</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/publications/2024/amico2024tracing-opioids-across/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/publications/2024/amico2024tracing-opioids-across/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Adapting to disruptions: Managing supply chain resilience through product rerouting</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/publications/2024/amico2024adapting-to-disruptions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/publications/2024/amico2024adapting-to-disruptions/</guid><description>See our blog post on this research.</description></item><item><title>Paper on Supply Chain Resilience Published in Science Advances</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/2024_01_resilience-published/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/2024_01_resilience-published/</guid><description>Excited to share our research published in Science Advances, focusing on a vital aspect of modern logistics: pharmaceutical supply chain resilience (Link to Paper 📑).
The COVID-19 pandemic and subsequent global events have underscored the critical need to enhance supply chain resilience. To address this challenge, our study introduces the concept of &amp;lsquo;reroute flexibility,&amp;rsquo; best understood through an analogy to a road network.
Picture a distribution network for products as a network of roads and intersections.</description></item></channel></rss>