<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Social Software Engineering on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-december-2023/</link><description>Recent content in Social Software Engineering on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-december-2023/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Quantifying the /Social/ in Social Software Engineering</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/schweitzer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/schweitzer/</guid><description>Abstract Open source software repositories offer high resolution data about the collaboration of developers. These data are not only of interest for software engineering, they also benefit management and organization science. Thanks to the open source Python package git2net we are able to extract co-editing networks from git repositories. Combining network measures with fine grained analyses of code changes, we are able to quantify the productivity of developers, their coordination effort, and the resilience of OSS projects against the drop-out of core developers.</description></item><item><title>The rise and fall of the social software engineer</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/storey/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/storey/</guid><description>Abstract Over the past few decades, software development has transitioned from a predominantly solo activity where developers create small stand alone programs, to a widespread distributed activity where hundreds and even thousands of developers operate within an online participatory community of practice to create complex software ecosystems. This large scale distributed development effort has been made possible by innovations that include the Internet, the World Wide Web, sophisticated development tools and agents, and rich communication channels and social media.</description></item><item><title>The Triadic Nature Of Code Review</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/bacchelli/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/bacchelli/</guid><description>Abstract This talk explores the multifaceted nature of code review in software development, delving into its three core dimensions: technical, social, and cognitive. While commonly perceived as a straightforward process aimed at bug detection, the talk will show how code review plays a broader role, significantly impacting knowledge transfer, team dynamics, and shared code ownership. In addressing the triadic nature of code review, we will discuss its evolution from a tool for code inspection to a critical element of social software engineering.</description></item></channel></rss>