<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Systems Design Bottom Up</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/design/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/design/</guid><description>Two short texts for the general audience explain the problems of systems design in complex systems:
Designing Systems Bottom Up: Facets and Problems
The Bigger Picture: Complexity Meets Systems Design</description></item><item><title>Summary Documents and the Secrets they Hold -- Part 2</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_5-summarydocs_part2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_5-summarydocs_part2/</guid><description>Summary documents are one of our main sources for the Project 130 Years of Swiss Parliament. As highlighted in Part 1 of our series on Summary Documents, we extract a lot of information from these documents. Most importantly, these documents are our baseline for the complete list of bills presented to parliament. They also include information about cosponsorship signatures, which can be used to study legislative collaborations and alliances.
In this blogpost we talk about the numbering of bills as well as presenting some exceptions that caused us some headaches when exporting and structuring their information.</description></item><item><title>Theory of social roles</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/theory_of_social_roles_in_networks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/theory_of_social_roles_in_networks/</guid><description>Our new paper A new theory of social roles in networks is available now.
Individuals fulfill different social roles in different contexts. For example, a professor teaches in a lecture theatre and does research in the lab. Especially in large networks, this context is very heterogenous as local clusters form. If these clusters are not addressed role detection yields flawed results. We address the effect of clusters on roles in networks with a novel theory of social roles.</description></item><item><title>Historical Network research lunch lecture</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/hnr_lunch_lecture/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/hnr_lunch_lecture/</guid><description>Ramona Roller presents how to treat time in a letter correspondence network of the Reformation.
The Reformation is characterised by frequent letter correspondences between scholars which can be modeled as a network. Letters have sending dates, providing a temporal order for the spread of ideas and routes of influence. This temporal order of letters affects network measures and therefore has to be considered in network analyses. I show how to address this challenge by using pathpy a software to analyse temporal networks.</description></item><item><title>Summary Documents and the Secrets they Hold -- Part 1</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_4-summarydocs_part1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_4-summarydocs_part1/</guid><description>One of our main data sources for our Project 130 Years of Swiss Parliament (click here for the project overview) are so-called summary of proceedings documents. The Amtliches Bulltin publishes summary documents (dt. Übersicht der Verhandlungen or summary of proceedings) for each parliamentary session. These documents contain a list of proposed bills by the members of parliament along with additional information (date of submission, bill text, committee assignments, co-sponsorship, and dates of important decisions).</description></item><item><title>Where did we all go wrong?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/wisdom/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 15:30:44 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/wisdom/</guid><description>The wisdom of crowds can fail under social influence. Two new papers finally got accepted:
Enhanced or distorted wisdom of crowds? An agent-based model of opinion formation under social influence, forthcoming in: Swarm Intelligence (2021)
The ambiguous role of social influence on the wisdom of crowds: An analytic approach, in: Physica A (2021) 567:125624
A, rather indirect, contribution to the discussion about corona related measures.</description></item><item><title>A new data source: Records of the Swiss Parliament</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_3-datasources/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_3-datasources/</guid><description>Our DemocraSci project builds on three data sources.
The Amtliches Bulletin, containing word protocols/proceedings from both chambers Summary of Proceedings, containing an overview over all discussed/submitted bills (dt. Geschäfte) Additional Protocols, containing additional word protocols from sessions recorded between 1921 and 1970. The documentation of the Swiss parliamentary sessions are recorded in the Amtliches Bulletin. These documentations of the sessions have undergone three mayor changes since the foundation of the Swiss Federal Assembly in 1848.</description></item><item><title>Open Position</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/open_position_hiwimarch2021/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/open_position_hiwimarch2021/</guid><description>We are looking for 1-2 student research assistants to work on our data project &amp;ldquo;DemocraSci – a research platform for data-driven democracy studies in Switzerland&amp;rdquo; and our SNF-project. The projects use almost 130 years of Swiss parliamentary data to create a comprehensive and searchable database on Swiss politics. The hired student(s) will assist the projects by creating intermediary data bases and various coding tasks. Good programming skills (python, database skills) are a must.</description></item><item><title>GAMBIT: Name disambiguation for VCS</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/gambit-an-open-source-name-disambiguation-tool-for-version-control-systems/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 18:25:23 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/gambit-an-open-source-name-disambiguation-tool-for-version-control-systems/</guid><description>We are excited to announce that our paper gambit - An Open Source Name Disambiguation Tool for Version Control Systems has been accepted at MSR 2021.
The ease of creating user accounts online results in single individuals appearing under multiple aliases. If these ambiguities are not adequately resolved, subsequent studies can be significantly biased. gambit enables researches to disambiguate an individual&amp;rsquo;s different aliases to a unique identifier and therefore represents an essential first step in any study analysing real-world user data.</description></item><item><title>GHYPERNET in the top 40!</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/ghypernet_in_top_40/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 12:02:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/ghypernet_in_top_40/</guid><description>The RStudio blog has listed our ghypernet R package in the top 40 picks of May 2020!
May 2020: &amp;ldquo;Top 40&amp;rdquo; New CRAN Packages
The library allows studying multi-edge networks using the framework of the generalised hypergeometric ensemble of random graphs. Install the package by running install.packages('ghypernet') in R, or go to ghyper.net for more information.</description></item><item><title>LR test for network models</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/likelihood_ratio_test/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 11:32:31 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/likelihood_ratio_test/</guid><description>Did you know that Wilk&amp;rsquo;s theorem does not hold for multi-edge network models?
In our newest preprint, we show how to correct the null-distribution of the likelihood-ratio test when working with complex network data. Check out the paper here.</description></item><item><title>Fragile yet resilient: Published!</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/fragile_yet_resilient/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 11:17:55 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/fragile_yet_resilient/</guid><description>The article Fragile, Yet Resilient: Adaptive Decline in a Collaboration Network of Firms has been published on Frontiers in Applied Mathematics and Statistics. You can find it here.</description></item><item><title>Spatial Humanities Workshop</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/spatial_humanities_workshop/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/spatial_humanities_workshop/</guid><description>Ramona Roller presents extraction and use of geo-spatial data on territories of the Holy Roman Empire. These data can be used to analyze the European reformation of the 16th century.
The workshop &amp;lsquo;Geography meets Digital Humanities: Neuere Ansätze raumbezogener Modellierung&amp;rsquo; addresses the question of how to use &amp;lsquo;space&amp;rsquo; in scientific analyses in the Digital Humanities. Definitions of &amp;lsquo;space&amp;rsquo; range from interpretative frameworks to geographic notations. Ramona presents a novel data set comprising geo-spatial attributes of territories of the Holy Roman Empire in the 16th century.</description></item><item><title>Co-Sponsorship Networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_2-snf-project/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_2-snf-project/</guid><description>Starting in 2019, we were granted an SNF-research project to study how members of the Swiss parliament shaped the Swiss political landscape.
Project details
funding agency: Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF) duration: 36 months (2019-2022) Project summary
Analyses of legislative behavior is often based on ideological positions (or policy preferences) of the involved actors, such as parties or individual members of parliament (MPs). These positions allow for detailed analysis on how political alliances are formed and leveraged to influence the decision-making process in their favour.</description></item><item><title>SDSC Project: DemocraSci</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_1-sdsc-project/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_1-sdsc-project/</guid><description>The goal of our research and data project DemocraSci is to create a searchable database of the Swiss Parliament. For the past 130 years (starting in 1891), the Swiss Parliament has carefully documented its actions and debates in the so-called Amtliches Bulletin&amp;mdash;a stenographic record of parliamentary speeches and legislative proposals. In our project we carefully extract and structure the data from the Amtliches Bulletin.
Our database will contain
all bills, legislative proposals and parliamentary questions brought forth by members of the parliament, comittees, parliamentary groups (called Fraktionen) and cantons (in the form of a Standesinitative) all speeches recorded in the Amtliches Bulletin all members passing through the parliament as well as their functions, their committee memberships and their involvement in parliamentary affairs all votes and voting outcomes for proposals all cosponsorship signatures from members of parliament on bills The project is a collaboration between our chair and the Swiss Data Science Center, SDSC.</description></item><item><title>Scientific Networks and Success</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/acs_call_for_papers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/acs_call_for_papers/</guid><description>Researchers along with their research institutions are increasingly evaluated according to scientific performance metrics. Yet how should they be measured? And is the required data available? Also, Modern research is predominantly a team endeavor in which success and failure strongly depends on social forces among collaborators driven by intrinsic and extrinsic motivators, behavior and strategy. Do we have the right models to account for these phenomena?
If these questions drive your research, you are interested in our Special Issue on Scientific Networks and Success.</description></item><item><title>Should the government reward cooperation?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/should-the-government-reward-cooperation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/should-the-government-reward-cooperation/</guid><description>We derive analytical expressions for the critical bonus needed to make cooperation as attractive as defection. We show that for one information regime the critical bonus increases with the level of cooperation, while in a second regime the bonus decreases with the level of cooperation. In this second regime, full cooperation can be achieved once a cold-start problem is solved. See our paper here.</description></item><item><title>How do you quantify firms importance?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/quantifying-the-importance-of-firms-by-means-of-reputation-and-network-control/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/quantifying-the-importance-of-firms-by-means-of-reputation-and-network-control/</guid><description>The reputation of firms is largely channeled through their ownership structure. We use this relation to determine reputation spillovers between transnational companies and their participated companies in an ownership network core of 1318 firms. We then apply concepts of network controllability to identify minimum sets of driver nodes (MDS) of 314 firms in this network. See our paper here.</description></item><item><title>SNS2020 program is online</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/sns2020-program-is-online/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/sns2020-program-is-online/</guid><description>The program of our Satellite Workshop Scientific Networks and Success of CCS 2020 is online. It will take place online on December 9, 2020. You can also download the poster of the Satellite.</description></item><item><title>Do HONs gauge temporal controllability?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/higher-order-models-capture-changes-in-controllability-of-temporal-networks/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/higher-order-models-capture-changes-in-controllability-of-temporal-networks/</guid><description>Our paper Higher-order models capture changes in controllability of temporal networks has been accepted to be published in Journal of Physics: Complexity</description></item><item><title>New theory explains political polarization</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/new-theory-explains-political-polarization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/new-theory-explains-political-polarization/</guid><description>Scientists at the CSH expand an old theory of balance to explain the emergence of hyperpolarization
A new model of opinion formation shows how the extent to which people like or dislike each other affects their political views ?and vice versa. The resulting division of societies can even become a matter of life and death, as the current crises show.
A Weighted Balance Model of Opinion Hyperpolarization</description></item><item><title>Scientific Networks and Success</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/scientific-networks-and-success/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/scientific-networks-and-success/</guid><description>Every researcher is affected by how scientific performance is measured. How should it be measured? Do we have the right data to do it?
If you eager to have answers to these questions, come to our Satellite Workshop Scientific Networks and Success of CCS 2020.</description></item><item><title>HONS2020 program is online</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/hons2020-program-is-online/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/hons2020-program-is-online/</guid><description>The program of our HONS satellite at NetSci 2020 is online here. It will take place online on September 17, 2020.
HONS is the NetSci satellite for researchers that try to understand what we miss when we analyze graphs and network abstractions of complex systems. Its focus is on cutting-edge Higher-Order Network modelling techniques, which generalize network science techniques to models that account for higher-order dependencies in data on real systems.</description></item><item><title>Network Analysis in R</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/network-analysis-in-r/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/network-analysis-in-r/</guid><description>The latest version of our R library ghypernet is available on CRAN.
The library allows studying multi-edge networks using the framework of the generalised hypergeometric ensemble of random graphs. Install the package by running install.packages('ghypernet') in R, or go to ghyper.net for more information.</description></item><item><title>Lead Agency Project granted</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/leadagency/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/leadagency/</guid><description>We are happy to announce that our Lead Agency Project &amp;ldquo;Signed Relations and Structural Balance in Complex Systems: From Data to Models&amp;rdquo; was granted by the SNF and NCN. We will carry out this project together with Prof. Holyst&amp;rsquo;s group of Physics in Economy and Social Sciences at Warsaw University of Technology (Faculty of Physics).</description></item><item><title>What is a model and why do we need it?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/what-is-a-model-and-why-do-we-need-it/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/what-is-a-model-and-why-do-we-need-it/</guid><description>A contribution by Ramona Roller was published on March 12, 2020 on the blog of the Digital Humanities Association in German-speaking countries. You can find the blog post here.</description></item><item><title>Let's spend the night together?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/lets-spend-the-night-together/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/lets-spend-the-night-together/</guid><description>Bechstein&amp;rsquo;s bats form groups of different size to spend the day together in several roosts. At dusk, these groups dissolve, at dawn they may re-merge. So, what is a typical group size? And how long does a group use the same roost? We answer these questions by analyzing empirical data from two colonies. What is more, we also provide an agent-based model to reproduce these findings. See our paper here.</description></item><item><title>Who are the leaders and followers among bats?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/who-are-the-leaders-and-followers-among-bats/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/who-are-the-leaders-and-followers-among-bats/</guid><description>Bats don&amp;rsquo;t tell! But we find out. See our two new manuscripts here: paper 1, paper 2</description></item><item><title>Improving the robustness of online social networks: A simulation approach of network interventions</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/robust_sn/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/robust_sn/</guid><description>Online social networks (OSN) are prime examples of socio-technical systems in which individuals interact via a technical platform. We study the emergence of large drop-out cascades of users leaving the OSN by means of an agent-based model. Our aim is to prevent such drop-out cascades by influencing specific agents. We identify strategies to control agents such that drop-out cascades are significantly reduced, and the robustness of the OSN is increased. Read more on arXiv.</description></item><item><title>The law of proportionate growth and its siblings</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/the-law-of-proportionate-growth-and-its-siblings/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/the-law-of-proportionate-growth-and-its-siblings/</guid><description>We combine the law of proportionate growth with additive growth terms, to develop an agent-based modeling framework with vast applications in social and economic systems. The paper discusses phenomena as diverse as saturated growth, competition, stochastic growth, investments in random environments, wealth redistribution, opinion dynamics and the wisdom of crowds, reputation dynamics, knowledge growth, and the combination with network dynamics. Read more on ArXiv</description></item></channel></rss>