<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Team on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/</link><description>Recent content in Team on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/georges_andres/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/georges_andres/</guid><description>Interests My current research topics are centered around structural balance theory and opinion formation in social systems. During my Master&amp;rsquo;s in physics at the ETHZ I encountered the study of complex systems via network representations and agent based models. The fascination for this line of research lead me to pursue a PhD at the Chair of Systems Design.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giuseppe_russo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giuseppe_russo/</guid><description>Interests I am fascinated by interdisciplinary questions in Computational Social Science and Applied NLP. After completing a MSc in Computer Science at ETH, I worked at IBM exploring NLP applications to medical domain. My current interest in based on applying NLP to ideology detection to frame alliances and opinions.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/sophia-schlosser/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/sophia-schlosser/</guid><description>Prior to joining the chair of Systems Design, Sophia received a Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in Communications and Political Science from the University of Zürich, and a Master&amp;rsquo;s degree in International Affairs from the Hertie School of Governance in Berlin and the Graduate Institute in Geneva. Sophia&amp;rsquo;s research interests focus on political networks, in particular covering political polarization dynamics, the professionalization processes of parliaments, and in general the science-policy nexus.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ambra_amico/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ambra_amico/</guid><description>Before joining the Chair, I received a Master degree in physics at la Sapienza University in Rome, where I got interested in the complex systems field. During my master thesis I applied inference methods and machine learning techniques to study human perception of facial beauty. Currently, my research interests focus on cascade processes, namely I am studying how a local shock, appeared in a system, affects its different parts. By adopting a network perspective I can measure the cascade size and identify the possible characteristics of the system that prevent a big cascade size.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/christian_zingg/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/christian_zingg/</guid><description>In my research, I study the effects that shocks have on the network structure of social systems. To examine structural changes, I define and analyze measures that are, for example, based on entropies. Having a theoretical background yet being interested in real-world problems, it is essential to me to discuss both theory and applications.
Before starting as a PhD at the Chair of Systems Design, I studied applied mathematics at the ETH Zurich.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/</guid><description>I am a Ph.D. candidate at the Chair of Systems design at ETH Zurich where I work on data-driven models of socio-historical systems. Currently, I focus on a temporal network model of letter correspondences during the European Reformation. I try to understand the underlying communication patterns which gave rise to the spreading of ideas at that time. Specifically challenging in this respect are the sampling bias of the data, as not all historical artifacts are equally likely to survive over time, and capturing the temporal sequence in which historical actions occurred.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/christoph_gote/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/christoph_gote/</guid><description>Postdoctoral Researcher at the Chair of Systems Design at ETH Zurich, Switzerland. My current research focuses on the analysis of collaboration structures in software development teams. To this end, I apply data-driven modelling and network analysis to large sets repositories of Open Source Software (OSS) projects. I further develops tools to facilitate the extraction of information from OSS repositories, as well as methods for temporal- and higher-order network analysis.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/laurence_brandenberger/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/laurence_brandenberger/</guid><description>I study legislative behavior and parliamentary networks. I am particularly interested in the temporal dynamics of political actors working together, for instance looking at how long it takes for a member of parliament to reciprocate a favor by a colleague. Furthermore, I study how political actors change their political positions over time and influence each other.
As a quantitative social scientist, I use Relational Event Models (REMs), Exponential Random Graph Models (ERGMs) and temporal variations thereof (so-called TERGMs or BTERGMs) and conventional regressions for my analyses.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/luca_verginer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/luca_verginer/</guid><description>I am a Postdoc at che Chair of Systems Design at ETH Zürich and hold a Ph.D. in Economics and Data Science from IMT Lucca.
I am an empirical economist and network scientist studying through econometrics, numerical simulations, and network models issues related to intellectual property, supply chain resilience and high skill labour mobility, among (many) other subjects. I am passionate about data in all its forms (and sizes) and constantly looking for curious and ingenious ways to visualize, collect and extract value from it.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giacomo_vaccario/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giacomo_vaccario/</guid><description>Giacomo is a senior researcher at the Chair of Systems Design, ETH Zurich. In this group, he worked as a post-doc and obtained a Doctorate in Science in 2019. Before joining ETH Zurich, he completed the Part III of the Mathematical Tripos from the University of Cambridge and received a Master in Theoretical Physics from Sapienza University of Rome.
Giacomo&amp;rsquo;s research interests lie in understanding the determinants and effects of cooperation in socio-economic systems.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giona_casiraghi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giona_casiraghi/</guid><description>Research Interests I work on two tighly connected topics. How to define and quantify resilience, in complex systems in general and in social organisations in particular. How to model complex systems from the data, to perform a data-driven study of their properties.
Resilience of Social Organisations We aim at an understanding of how different online social organisations withstand and recover from internal and external shocks, and how such a resilience can be improved.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/nadja_taras/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/nadja_taras/</guid><description>Administrative Assistant
office days: Monday, Tuesday, Friday
+41 044 632 83 51</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/frank_schweitzer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/frank_schweitzer/</guid><description>Short Bio
Editorial Boards
Participation in Committees - Studienkommission - Berufungskommission - Informatikkommission -- Talks
Program Committee
Books
Before 2005
Private Website (in German)</description></item></channel></rss>