<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Team on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/</link><description>Recent content in Team on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Giuseppe Russo</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giuseppe_russo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giuseppe_russo/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="interests">Interests&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I am fascinated by interdisciplinary questions in Computational Social Science and Applied NLP. After completing a MSc in Computer Science at ETH, I worked at IBM exploring NLP applications to medical domain.
My current interest in based on applying NLP to ideology detection to frame alliances and opinions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sophia Schlosser</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/sophia-schlosser/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/sophia-schlosser/</guid><description>&lt;p>Prior to joining the chair of Systems Design for her doctorate, Sophia received a Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in Communications and Political Science from the University of Zürich, and a Master&amp;rsquo;s degree in International Affairs from the Hertie School of Governance in Berlin and the Graduate Institute in Geneva.
Sophia&amp;rsquo;s research interests focus on political networks, in particular covering political polarization dynamics, the professionalization processes of parliaments, and the science-policy nexus.
Her doctoral dissertation focussed on how to best apply current NLP methods to study legislative dynamics of the Swiss Federal Asembly from 1891 to today.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Georges Andres</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/georges_andres/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/georges_andres/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="interests">Interests&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My current research topics are centered around structural balance theory and opinion formation in social systems. During my Master&amp;rsquo;s in physics at the ETHZ I encountered the study of complex systems via network representations and agent based models. The fascination for this line of research lead me to pursue a PhD at the Chair of Systems Design.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ambra Amico</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ambra_amico/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ambra_amico/</guid><description>&lt;p>I am a Postdoctoral researcher at the Chair of Systems Design at ETH Zurich, where I completed my PhD in 2023 under the guidance of Prof. Frank Schweitzer.
With a background in physics, I got fascinated by the field of complex systems and its interface with economics and social sciences.
My current research is centred around large-scale supply chains, specifically focusing on the dynamics of distribution systems.
I am interested in devising novel strategies to enhance their resilience against disruptions.
Recognizing the profound impact of their complex topology on resilience, I am also intrigued by the mechanisms governing these systems&amp;rsquo; formation and how they give rise to the observed structures.
My approach combines large-scale empirical analysis with formal modeling techniques borrowed from complexity science.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Christian Zingg</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/christian_zingg/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/christian_zingg/</guid><description>&lt;p>My research examines the impact that shocks such as the departure of key individuals have on social systems and their subsequent recovery.
I develop and analyse statistical resilience measures that are, for example, based on entropies and which are computationally efficient.
This enables me to study the resilience of systems with hundreds of individuals and analyse their evolution over multiple years.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The social systems that I study are primarily teams of Open Source Software developers on online platforms such as GitHub.
I follow a data-driven approach by mining and analysing hundreds of Gigabytes of data to track the interactions between developers based on their public activities.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Christoph Gote</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/christoph_gote/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/christoph_gote/</guid><description>&lt;p>Christoph Gote is a Postdoctoral Researcher at the Chair of Systems Design at ETH Zurich and at the Data Analytics Group at the University of Zurich. His research focuses on the analysis of collaboration structures in software development teams. To this end, he develops tools, such as git2net and gambit, that facilitate the extraction and cleaning of action and interaction data from git repositories. From these actions and interactions, he subsequently derives fine-grained social and technical networks. Based on these networks, he studies topics such as the optimal size for teams, the relationship between coordination structures and team productivity, the emergence of hierarchies, and team resilience. For this research, he applies a broad range of methods from data-driven modelling, statistics, machine learning, and network analysis. In addition, he develops state-of-the-art techniques for temporal-, higher-, and multi-order network analysis.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ramona Roller</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/ramona_roller/</guid><description>&lt;p>I am a postdoc at the Chair of Systems Design at ETH Zurich, where I study societal transitions and communication networks.
I am particular interested in how European society in the 16th century changed as a result of the Reformation, a social movement that overthrew the Catholic Church.
For example, I analyse how scholars specialised in their communication roles and why territories adopted Protestantism.
A central aim of my research is to understand the driving factors of transitions, accounting for interdependencies and heterogeneities in complex social systems.
This is achieved by merging analytical tools and concepts from various disciplines such as Social Network Analysis, Event History Models, Potential Outcome Model of causality, and conventional regressions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Giacomo Vaccario</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giacomo_vaccario/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giacomo_vaccario/</guid><description>&lt;p>Giacomo is a senior researcher at the Chair of Systems Design, ETH Zurich.
In this group, he worked as a post-doc and obtained a Doctorate in Science in 2019.
Before joining ETH Zurich, he completed the Part III of the Mathematical Tripos from the University of Cambridge and received a Master in Theoretical Physics from Sapienza University of Rome.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Giacomo&amp;rsquo;s research interests lie in understanding the determinants and effects of cooperation in socio-economic systems.
He studies &lt;a href="https://epjdatascience.springeropen.com/articles/10.1140/epjds/s13688-017-0117-5">how collaborations are established&lt;/a> among firms or scientists to create new knowledge.
He also investigates how the knowledge of these actors, in turn, &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00191-018-0569-1">defines their collaborations&lt;/a>.
To capture this feedback, he combines statistical analysis of patent and publication data with agent-based models.
In recent years, he has worked extensively on how psychological and cognitive processes can foster but also hamper the &lt;a href="https://www.worldscientific.com/doi/abs/10.1142/S0219525920500186">emergence of cooperation&lt;/a>.
To this end, he has developed mathematical models and experiments leveraging game theory and complex systems theory.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Luca Verginer</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/luca_verginer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/luca_verginer/</guid><description>&lt;p>I am an empirical economist and network scientist focused on the dynamics of &lt;em>pharmaceutical supply chains&lt;/em> and the role of patenting in their &lt;em>innovation&lt;/em>. My research ambitiously spans both economic and social networks, using a diverse methodological toolkit that includes causal inference, advanced econometrics, and state-of-the-art neural network models, particularly Graph Neural Networks (GNN) and Natural Language Processing (NLP). A significant aspect of my work is dedicated to examining and enhancing the resilience of pharmaceutical supply chains. With a strong emphasis on &lt;em>temporal network&lt;/em> analysis. My reseaerch is directed towards shaping resilient, efficient, and innovative solutions for the challenges facing global health today.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Giona Casiraghi</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giona_casiraghi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/giona_casiraghi/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="research-interests">Research Interests&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I work on two tighly connected topics.
How to define and quantify resilience, in complex systems in general and in social organisations in particular.
How to model complex systems from the data, to perform a data-driven study of their properties.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="resilience-of-social-organisations">Resilience of Social Organisations&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>We aim at an understanding of how different online social organisations withstand and recover from internal and external shocks, and how such a resilience can be improved.
To do, so we investigate how different resilience metrics can be computed from data.
Our research is deeply rooted in data science and the data-driven modelling of complex systems.
We use and develop new methodologies from network science, multivariate statistics, machine learning, and statistical physics.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Laurence Brandenberger</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/laurence_brandenberger/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/laurence_brandenberger/</guid><description>&lt;p>I study legislative politics and political networks. I am particularly interested in the temporal dynamics of political actors working together, for instance looking at how long it takes for a member of parliament to reciprocate a favor by a colleague. Furthermore, I study how political actors change their political positions over time and influence each other.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am a quantitative social scientist who loves using computational tools (such as NER, ML or word embeddings) to enhance my insights into substantive research questions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Nadja Taras</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/nadja_taras/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/nadja_taras/</guid><description>&lt;p>Administrative Assistant&lt;/p>
&lt;p>office days: Monday, Tuesday, Friday&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+41 044 632 83 51&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Frank Schweitzer</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/frank_schweitzer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/team/frank_schweitzer/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/extra/fs/cv/">Short Bio&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/extra/fs/boards">Editorial Boards&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;!--
&lt;details>
&lt;summary>Participation in Committees&lt;/summary>

- Studienkommission
- Berufungskommission
- Informatikkommission

&lt;/details>
-->
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/extra/fs/talks/">Talks&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/extra/fs/pc/">Program Committee&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/books/">Books&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="until2005/">Before 2005&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.simply-complex.net">Private Website (in German)&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>