<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Complexity of Social and Economic Systems: From Models to Measures on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-final-symposium-october-2024/</link><description>Recent content in The Complexity of Social and Economic Systems: From Models to Measures on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-final-symposium-october-2024/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Abschiedsvorlesung Prof. Frank Schweitzer</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session04/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session04/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Coordination, Collaboration and Success</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session01/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session01/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Dependency, Risk and Resilience</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session02/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session02/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Emotions, Opinions and Polarization</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session03/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session03/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Complexity of Social Polarization: Connecting Individual Opinions and Societal Dynamics with Agent-Based Models and Experiments</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-1-flache/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-1-flache/</guid><description>Abstract Recently, many societies seem to shift towards more polarization and volatility in opinions, for example in attitudes about immigration or climate change. Underlying reasons of this development are hard to unravel. A key obstacle is that opinion dynamics in society involve a complex micro-macro interaction between interpersonal processes, meso-level conditions such as network structures, and macro-level outcomes, such as polarization in opinion distributions. Agent-based simulation models (ABM) offer powerful tools to address this challenge.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-3-vaccario/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-3-vaccario/</guid><description>Abstract</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-4-scholtes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-4-scholtes/</guid><description>Abstract The convergence of social and technical systems provides us with a wealth of log data that capture the structure and dynamics of social organizations. It is tempting to utilize these data to better understand how social organizations evolve, how collaboration and communication patterns are related to their &amp;ldquo;success&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;failure&amp;rdquo;, and how the position of individuals in social networks affects their performance, motivation, and productivity.
Considering examples from Open Source Software communities, scientific collaborations and peer-review processes, in this talk I will show how publicly available online data can be used to better understand how human and social aspects influence the success or failure of individuals as well as social organizations.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-3-battiston/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-3-battiston/</guid><description>Abstract</description></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/cbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/cbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/cbreak_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/cbreak_2/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Cascade Processes for Sparse Machine Learning</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-2-burkholz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-2-burkholz/</guid><description>Abstract What could seemingly distinct phenomena like a financial crisis, a global pandemic, or the sudden increase of wheat prizes have in common? On an abstract level, they all can emerge as result of a cascade process that evolves on a complex network of interdependent actors. Another well known example of a cascade process, yet, largely disregarded in the context of systemic risk analyses, is the evaluation of a deep neural network, i.</description></item><item><title>Closing Remarks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/4-0-garcia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/4-0-garcia/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Decoding Collaboration: Predicting and Optimising Software Development through Networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-2-gote/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-2-gote/</guid><description>Abstract How can we predict and optimise the performance of software development teams? This talk addresses this question by leveraging insights from network science to explore the complex interplay between the technical and social structures of software projects. Looking back on the past 20 years at the Chair of Systems Design, we delve into how changes in project structure and team dynamics impact collaboration and success. By studying both open-source and proprietary software development, we examine how growth, developer turnover, and interactions shape both the technical evolution of software and the social fabric of the teams behind it.</description></item><item><title>Extreme Events in Micro- and Macroeconomic Dynamics: Theory and Empirical Evidence</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-1-napoletano/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-1-napoletano/</guid><description>Abstract The dynamics of real-world economies are characterized by various types of extreme events, which are typically more relevant than what is predicted by a Gaussian distribution. The talk will present recent evidence about the importance of these extreme events for the dynamics of countries’ GDP and the dynamics of firms and asset prices. It will also show how agent-based models, emphasizing network interactions of heterogeneous agents can be used to explain the emergence of extreme events in various economic domains.</description></item><item><title>Lunch Break</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/lbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/lbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Memory, Causality and Their Consequences in Temporal Networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-1-karsai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-1-karsai/</guid><description>Abstract Temporal networks are commonly used to represent systems where connections between elements are active only for restricted periods of time, such as in telecommunication systems, biochemical reactions or social networks. Such time-varying interactions may be biased by local correlations between causally related events and commonly influenced by memory effects, which in turn lead to the emergence of mesoscale temporal motifs, long time-respecting paths, and bursty interaction dynamics. In these talk we will address the consequences of memory driven and casually related interactions on the emerging network structure and on the outcome of ongoing dynamical processes.</description></item><item><title>Online emotions and how to measure them</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-4-garcia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-4-garcia/</guid><description>Abstract Our online life generates a vast amount of digital traces, for example when we use our phone or talk with others on social media. These traces can be used to study aspects of emotional life that were very difficult to study with experiments or surveys. I will present work on the development and application of digital trace data analysis to study emotions at various levels. I will present LEIA, a language model to identify individual emotions from social media text and how text analysis methods can be applied to create emotion macroscopes of society at large.</description></item><item><title>Opinion Distributions in the Real World</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-2-lorenz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-2-lorenz/</guid><description>Abstract Models and mechanisms for the dynamics of opinion dynamics are an intriguing topic where complex systems research wants to contribute to our understanding of the phenomenon of polarization. A problem is that social processes and in particular opinion dynamics in the real world do not unfold in isolation, also other factors than just local interaction about opinions determine the opinions of individuals. In the talk I will present opinion distributions from movie ratings and attitude surveys and showcase some directions for a complementary more data-driven modeling approach.</description></item><item><title>Quantifying Resilience in Complex Systems: From Robustness to Adaptivity</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-4-casiraghi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-4-casiraghi/</guid><description>Abstract Real-world systems are inherently adaptive, capable of recovering and reorganising after disruptions. To truly understand and enhance resilience, we must quantify such adaptivity. Achieving this requires high-resolution, real-time data and mathematical models that capture not only the impact of disruptions but also the system&amp;rsquo;s capacity to respond and change. By integrating agent-based models with network analytics, we can track disruptions as they occur, predict failure cascades, and design more effective recovery strategies.</description></item><item><title>The Rise of Extremes: Tracing the Surge in Swiss Political Polarization</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-3-brandenberger/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-3-brandenberger/</guid><description>Abstract Are we truly witnessing an era of unprecedented polarization? While many researchers contend that political polarization—particularly among elites—has intensified worldwide, much of the empirical research relies on short-term analyses. This begs the question: could elite polarization have fluctuated throughout history, following a natural ebb and flow?
In this talk, I explore the evolution of ideological polarization within the Swiss National Parliament, spanning from 1891 to the present. By constructing a unified ideological space, we trace party positions over the last 130 years.</description></item><item><title>Welcome and Introduction</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/0-0-opening/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/0-0-opening/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>