<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Complexity of Social and Economic Systems: From Models to Measures on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-final-symposium-october-2024/</link><description>Recent content in The Complexity of Social and Economic Systems: From Models to Measures on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-final-symposium-october-2024/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Abschiedsvorlesung Prof. Frank Schweitzer</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session04/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session04/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Coordination, Collaboration and Success</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session01/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session01/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Dependency, Risk and Resilience</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session02/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session02/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Emotions, Opinions and Polarization</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session03/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/session03/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Complexity of Social Polarization: Connecting Individual Opinions and Societal Dynamics with Agent-Based Models and Experiments</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-1-flache/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-1-flache/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="presentation-slides-pdfpresentation-flachepdf">&lt;a href="Presentation-Flache.pdf">Presentation Slides (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Recently, many societies seem to shift towards more polarization and volatility in opinions, for example in attitudes about immigration or climate change. Underlying reasons of this development are hard to unravel. A key obstacle is that opinion dynamics in society involve a complex micro-macro interaction between interpersonal processes, meso-level conditions such as network structures, and macro-level outcomes, such as polarization in opinion distributions. Agent-based simulation models (ABM) offer powerful tools to address this challenge. Different types of ABM will be presented that demonstrate how and under which conditions polarization and intergroup animosity could arise as unintended result of fundamental and prevalent interpersonal processes, for example homophily and social influence. Drawing on recent research, it will then be shown how competing models of polarization dynamics can be compared and informed with data from lab experiments and social network studies.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/cbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/cbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/cbreak_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/cbreak_2/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Abschiedsvorlesung: Dämmerung</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/5-0-schweitzer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/5-0-schweitzer/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="videoaufzeichnung">Videoaufzeichnung&lt;/h3>
&lt;iframe width="832" height="468"
src="https://video.ethz.ch/etc/designs/mmp/video/player.html?id=fa1c7d10-e7da-4721-beb5-dcf9faed4baa"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h3 id="presentation-slidesschweitzer-slideshtmlbr">&lt;a href="Schweitzer-Slides.html">Presentation Slides&lt;/a>&lt;br>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>(PgUp, PgDown to navigate, TAB for overview)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cascade Processes for Sparse Machine Learning</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-2-burkholz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-2-burkholz/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>What could seemingly distinct phenomena like a financial crisis, a global pandemic, or the sudden increase of wheat prizes have in common? On an abstract level, they all can emerge as result of a cascade process that evolves on a complex network of interdependent actors. Another well known example of a cascade process, yet, largely disregarded in the context of systemic risk analyses, is the evaluation of a deep neural network, i.e., the work horse of the ongoing revolution by modern machine learning and AI. We will discuss how fundamental insights into the nature of cascade dynamics cannot only guide the design of more robust systems but also inspire us to build efficient AI.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Climate change and financial risk</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-3-battiston/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-3-battiston/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="presentation-slides-pdfpresentation-battistonpdf">&lt;a href="Presentation-Battiston.pdf">Presentation Slides (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Climate change is one the defining emerging challenges of our times. The relation between climate change and finance is two-sided. On the one hand, climate change poses a new type of risk for finance, which traditional approaches are not well-suited to describe. On the other hand, finance’s perception of climate risk has an impact on investments that support climate change mitigation and adaptation. Therefore, an adequate assessment of climate risk by the financial sector is key to avoid under-investments in climate action. This talk provides an overview of the state-of-art on the subject and why it matters for citizens and academics outside the finance discipline.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Closing Remarks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/4-0-garcia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/4-0-garcia/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Decoding Collaboration: Predicting and Optimising Software Development through Networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-2-gote/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-2-gote/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="presentation-slides-pdfpresentation-gotepdf">&lt;a href="Presentation-Gote.pdf">Presentation Slides (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>How can we predict and optimise the performance of software development teams? This talk addresses this question by leveraging insights from network science to explore the complex interplay between the technical and social structures of software projects. Looking back on the past 20 years at the Chair of Systems Design, we delve into how changes in project structure and team dynamics impact collaboration and success. By studying both open-source and proprietary software development, we examine how growth, developer turnover, and interactions shape both the technical evolution of software and the social fabric of the teams behind it. The analysis reveals patterns that can help enhance team resilience and productivity, ensuring sustainable development in diverse software ecosystems. By the end of this presentation, you’ll gain a deeper understanding of how to utilise network analysis to predict key outcomes in software development and optimise collaboration for success.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Extreme Events in Micro- and Macroeconomic Dynamics: Theory and Empirical Evidence</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-1-napoletano/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-1-napoletano/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The dynamics of real-world economies are characterized by various types of extreme events, which are typically more relevant than what is predicted by a Gaussian distribution. The talk will present recent evidence about the importance of these extreme events for the dynamics of countries’ GDP and the dynamics of firms and asset prices. It will also show how agent-based models, emphasizing network interactions of heterogeneous agents can be used to explain the emergence of extreme events in various economic domains. These models can also be useful to study which policies can be more appropriate to deal with extreme economic risk and to improve the resilience of real-world economies and markets.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Knowledge in socio-economic systems: Insights from collaboration, mobility, and data-driven models</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-3-vaccario/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-3-vaccario/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="presentation-slides-pdfpresentation-vaccariopdf">&lt;a href="Presentation-Vaccario.pdf">Presentation Slides (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Knowledge plays a central role in shaping economics and science. In this talk, I will explore the structure, exchange, and transfer of knowledge in socio-economic systems. I will focus on collaborations between firms and scientists and how these interactions influence knowledge production. I will also examine how the knowledge possessed by these actors shapes their collaborations. My analysis will show that knowledge not only results from collaboration but also drives it. Additionally, I will reconstruct the transfer of tacit knowledge by analyzing scientists&amp;rsquo; mobility across institutes, cities, and countries. These patterns reveal temporal correlations that challenge traditional views of mobility networks and introduce the concept of &amp;ldquo;knowledge corridors.&amp;rdquo; To capture these dynamics, I will use a data-driven approach, combining statistical analyses of patent and publication data with empirically calibrated agent-based models. This will provide a comprehensive understanding of knowledge flow in complex collaborative systems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lunch Break</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/lbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/lbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Making of the Chair</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/z_making-of-the-chair/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/z_making-of-the-chair/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="take-your-seats">Take your seats&lt;/h2>
&lt;iframe width="832" height="468"
src="welcome.mp4"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h2 id="heading">&lt;/h2>
&lt;h2 id="social-capital-ko-autoren-netzwerk-ohne-fs">Social Capital: Ko-Autoren-Netzwerk ohne FS&lt;/h2>
&lt;iframe width="832" height="468"
src="output.mp4"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h2 id="heading-1">&lt;/h2>
&lt;h2 id="making-of-the-chair">Making of the Chair&lt;/h2>
&lt;iframe width="832" height="468"
src="making.mp4"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h2 id="heading-2">&lt;/h2></description></item><item><title>Memory, Causality and Their Consequences in Temporal Networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-1-karsai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-1-karsai/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Temporal networks are commonly used to represent systems
where connections between elements are active only for
restricted periods of time, such as in telecommunication
systems, biochemical reactions or social networks. Such
time-varying interactions may be biased by local
correlations between causally related events and commonly
influenced by memory effects, which in turn lead to the
emergence of mesoscale temporal motifs, long time-respecting
paths, and bursty interaction dynamics. In these talk we
will address the consequences of memory driven and casually
related interactions on the emerging network structure and
on the outcome of ongoing dynamical processes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Online emotions and how to measure them</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-4-garcia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-4-garcia/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Our online life generates a vast amount of digital traces,
for example when we use our phone or talk with others on
social media. These traces can be used to study aspects of
emotional life that were very difficult to study with
experiments or surveys. I will present work on the
development and application of digital trace data analysis
to study emotions at various levels. I will present LEIA, a
language model to identify individual emotions from social
media text and how text analysis methods can be applied to
create emotion macroscopes of society at large.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Opinion Distributions in the Real World</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-2-lorenz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-2-lorenz/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Models and mechanisms for the dynamics of opinion dynamics
are an intriguing topic where complex systems research wants
to contribute to our understanding of the phenomenon of
polarization. A problem is that social processes and in
particular opinion dynamics in the real world do not unfold
in isolation, also other factors than just local interaction
about opinions determine the opinions of individuals. In the
talk I will present opinion distributions from movie ratings
and attitude surveys and showcase some directions for a
complementary more data-driven modeling approach.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantifying Resilience in Complex Systems: From Robustness to Adaptivity</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-4-casiraghi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/2-4-casiraghi/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Real-world systems are inherently adaptive, capable of recovering and reorganising after disruptions.
To truly understand and enhance resilience, we must quantify such adaptivity.
Achieving this requires high-resolution, real-time data and mathematical models that capture not only the impact of disruptions but also the system&amp;rsquo;s capacity to respond and change.
By integrating agent-based models with network analytics, we can track disruptions as they occur, predict failure cascades, and design more effective recovery strategies.
This approach is especially crucial for infrastructures like drug supply chains, where real-time adaptation is key to mitigating shortages and ensuring the continuous delivery of pharmaceuticals to patients.
In this talk, we demonstrate how moving beyond static resilience measures allows us to develop more comprehensive metrics that capture a system’s robustness and adaptive capacity, providing deeper insights into how they withstand and recover from shocks.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Rise of Extremes: Tracing the Surge in Swiss Political Polarization</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-3-brandenberger/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/3-3-brandenberger/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Are we truly witnessing an era of unprecedented polarization? While many researchers contend that political polarization—particularly among elites—has intensified worldwide, much of the empirical research relies on short-term analyses. This begs the question: could elite polarization have fluctuated throughout history, following a natural ebb and flow?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this talk, I explore the evolution of ideological polarization within the Swiss National Parliament, spanning from 1891 to the present. By constructing a unified ideological space, we trace party positions over the last 130 years. Our findings suggest that today&amp;rsquo;s polarization levels are historically unmatched.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Welcome and Introduction</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/0-0-opening/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/0-0-opening/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="presentation-slides-pdfopening-scholtespdf">&lt;a href="Opening-Scholtes.pdf">Presentation Slides (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/h3></description></item><item><title>What makes teams successful? A Network Science Perspective</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-4-scholtes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_final_workshop_october/1-4-scholtes/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="presentation-slides-pdfpresentation-scholtespdf">&lt;a href="Presentation-Scholtes.pdf">Presentation Slides (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The convergence of social and technical systems provides us with a wealth of log data that capture the structure and dynamics of social organizations. It is tempting to utilize these data to better understand how social organizations evolve, how collaboration and communication patterns are related to their &amp;ldquo;success&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;failure&amp;rdquo;, and how the position of individuals in social networks affects their performance, motivation, and productivity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Considering examples from Open Source Software communities, scientific collaborations and peer-review processes, in this talk I will show how publicly available online data can be used to better understand how human and social aspects influence the success or failure of individuals as well as social organizations. I further exemplify how we can creatively use massive online data and network science methods to test hypotheses at the intersection of computational social science, organizational theory, and management science.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>