<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Talks_backup on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/</link><description>Recent content in Talks_backup on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Talk by Tiago Peixoto</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk_2022_peixoto/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk_2022_peixoto/</guid><description/></item><item><title>SG Talk by Prof. Christian Kuehn</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk-chrisitan-kuehn/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk-chrisitan-kuehn/</guid><description>Prof Chrisitan Kuehn from the Technical University of Munich will present his work on the Mathematical Foundations of Early-Warning Signs and Resilience.
Date: Wednesday, 12 October 2022 at 09:15 - 10:15 Room: HG E41 Title: Mathematical Foundations of Early-Warning Signs and Resilience Early warning signals (EWSs) are a group of statistical time-series signals which could be used to anticipate a critical transition before it is reached. EWSs are model-independent methods that have grown in popularity to support evidence of disease emergence and disease elimination.</description></item><item><title>SG Seminar by Prof. Animesh Mukherjee</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk-animesh-mukherjee/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk-animesh-mukherjee/</guid><description>Prof. Animesh Mukherjee from the Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur will present his work on the rise of hate content in online social media.
Title: The rise of hate content in online social media Date: Monday, 13 June 2022 at 11:00 - 12:00 Room: HG E 33.5 Abstract In this talk, I shall be discussing some of the projects that we have been doing in the analysis, detection, and mitigation of hate content in online social media.</description></item><item><title>Talk Sanjukta Krishnagopal</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk-sanjukta-krishnagopal/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 15:25:14 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk-sanjukta-krishnagopal/</guid><description>Sanjukta Krishnagopal from the University College London will present her work on higher order network representations.
Title: Investigating the community structure of complex interaction data through a simplicial complex formulation. Date: Wednesday, 16 March 2022 at 11:00 - 12:00 Room: HG E23 Abstract Community detection in complex networks has been very successful in understanding several systems where interactions are inherent. The conventional Laplacian encodes many dynamical properties of a network, including community structure and flow of information along the network.</description></item><item><title>SG Talk by Prof. Simone Righi</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk-simone-righi-opgg/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 10:40:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks_backup/talk-simone-righi-opgg/</guid><description>Prof Simone Righi from the University Ca&amp;rsquo;Foscari of Venice will present his work on Optional Public Goods Games.
Date: Thursday, 2 December 2021 at 16:00 - 17:30 Room: HG E23 Title: The role of loners, reputation and punishment: the evolution of cooperation in the Optional Public Goods Game Problems of cooperation have often been simplified to the choice between defection and cooperation, although in many situations an individual could opt out or walk away from a situation.</description></item></channel></rss>