<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Frank Schweitzer's Additional Content on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/fs/</link><description>Recent content in Frank Schweitzer's Additional Content on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/fs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Frank Schweiter's Books</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/fs/books/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/fs/books/</guid><description>Brownian Agents and Active Particles. On the Emergence of Complex Behavior in the Natural and Social Sciences Frank Schweitzer, Foreword by J. Doyne Farmer, Berlin: Springer (Springer Series in Synergetics), 2003, 420 pp. 192 illus. (ISBN 3-540-43938-2) more details
Modeling Complexity in Economic and Social Systems Frank Schweitzer (ed.) Singapore: World Scientific, 2002, 395 pp. (ISBN 981-238-034-5) more details
Evolution und Selbstorganisation in der Ökonomie/Evolution and Self-Organization in Economics Frank Schweitzer, Gerald Silverberg (Hrsg.</description></item><item><title>Frank Schweiter's Talks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/fs/talks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/fs/talks/</guid><description>DemocraSci - 127 Years of the Swiss Parliament (May 20, 2019) | Swiss Federal Archives, Berne, Switzerland
DemocraSci - Greetings from the Swiss Parliament (May 13, 2019) | Project Information Day, Swiss Data Science Center, Berne, Switzerland
Quantifying social systems: From insights to impact (April 26, 2019) | Symposium &amp;ldquo;Computational Social Science - Quo Vadis?&amp;rdquo;, Department of Informatics, University of Zurich, Switzerland
Activity Matters: An Agent-based Framework of Active Matter with Applications in Biological and Social Systems (Jan.</description></item><item><title>Program Committees - Conferences</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/fs/pc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/fs/pc/</guid><description>COMPLEX NETWORKS 2021 (The Tenth International Conference on Complex Networks and their Applications) Madrid, Spain, 30 November - 2 December 2021
IC2S2 2021 (7th International Conference on Computational Social Science) Zurich, Switzerland, 27 - 31 July 2021
ICAART (13th International Conference on Agents and Artificial Intelligence) Vienna, Austria, 4 - 6 February 2021
CCS 2020 (Conference on Complex Systems) ONLINE, 4 - 11 December</description></item></channel></rss>