<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>130 Years of Swiss Parliament on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/research/130-years-of-swiss-parliament/</link><description>Recent content in 130 Years of Swiss Parliament on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/research/130-years-of-swiss-parliament/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Processing Large-Scale Archival Records: The Case of the Swiss Parliamentary Records</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/publications/2024/salamanca2024processing/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/publications/2024/salamanca2024processing/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Open Student Project (6 weeks)</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_11_studentproject/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_11_studentproject/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We would like to find out if we can find evidence of polarization in politician&amp;rsquo;s use of language. Do opposing party members increasingly speak out on different viewpoints and engage differently in political issues? Does their use of language increasingly differ over time?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Along the recently published paper of Peterson and Spirling 2018, we would like to see if there is evidence of linguistic divergence in recent decades in speeches held by Democratic and Republican members of Congress.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>DemocraSci team: Marta Balode</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_10_marta/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_10_marta/</guid><description>&lt;p>After 2.5 years of working with us on DemocraSci, Marta Balode is leaving our group.
Marta joined our team in the spring of 2020 and throughout her Master&amp;rsquo;s studies has been working tirelessly on extracting all the bills from the &lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_4-summarydocs_part1/">Summary documents&lt;/a>.
Without her work, the project would not be where it is today!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="parsing-the-summary-documents">Parsing the summary documents&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Marta parsed all summary documents from 1891-1970. She processed 8,897 pages scanned by the Federal Archives and the Parliamentary Library.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>New open position for a Hiwi - starting September 2022</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/job_offer_scientific_assistant/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/job_offer_scientific_assistant/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are looking for a student research assistant to work on our data project “ DemocraSci – a research platform for data-driven democracy studies in Switzerland ” and our SNF project “ Analyzing Co-Sponsorship Networks from 129 Years of the Swiss Federal Assembly ”. The projects use almost 130 years of Swiss parliamentary data to create a comprehensive and searchable database on Swiss politics. The hired student will create a web portal to allow access to our database.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Voting Records of the Swiss Parliament</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_9_voting/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_9_voting/</guid><description>&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s have a closer look at how voting records are reported for the Swiss parliament. Since our DemocraSci database spans over 130 years, we examine how voting is reported from 1891 until today.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="voting-records-over-time">Voting records over time&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Voting records for the National Council and the Council of States are reported differently throughout the years (see Figure below).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="tikz_votingTimeline.png" alt="How voting records are reported from 1891 until today">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For the National Council, electronic voting was accepted in 1987 and enacted in 1994, ebbing the way for more detailed voting records.
Before the winter session of 1995, voting records are mainly reported as aggregated counts, i.e., reporting how many members are for or against a specific proposal or proposition.
Only if 30 MPs demanded roll-call voting, did the records reflect the names of the MPs voting for/against a proposal/proposition.
With the implementation of electronic voting, voting records became more accessible. However, at first, only final votes (Gesamt/Schlussabstimmung) were reported as roll-call votes, for the rest, aggregated vote counts were reported.
From the winter session 2007 onwards, all votes are reported as roll-call votes in the National Council.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Swiss Parliamentary Bills: An Overview</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_8_bills/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_8_bills/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Swiss parliament knows several instruments to enact political change. We refer to these instruments as parliamentary bills (dt. Geschäfte). While some of the bill types are used only to gather information or get insights from the executive branch (i.e., the federal council or the departments), others are used to propose legislative changes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this blogpost we present 9 types of bills and how they move through the parliament. For each bill, we detail 8 different (potential) phases the bill goes through from submission to enactment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Amtliches Bulletin: records of speeches, propositions and votes -- Part 2</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_7_ab/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_7_ab/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this blogpost we go into details on the information contained in the &lt;code>Amtliches Bulletin (AB)&lt;/code> and how we separate the different entities and label them.
In a follow-up blogpost we explain how we separate and label the different entities with the use of a newly developed software application (designed by the SDSC and our chair).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a reminder, the records of the Swiss parliament are documented in three different types of documents (see our blogpost on this &lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_3-datasources/">here&lt;/a>).
While the summary documents contain an overview over all discussed bills (described in detail &lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_4-summarydocs_part1/">here (Part 1)&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_5-summarydocs_part2/">here (Part 2)&lt;/a>), the &lt;em>Amtliches Bulletin&lt;/em> is our main source for parliamentary speeches and votes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Amtliches Bulletin: records of speeches, propositions and votes -- Part 1</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_6-nrdocuments/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_6-nrdocuments/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this blogpost we give an overview over the information contained in the &lt;code>Amtliches Bulletin&lt;/code>&amp;mdash;our second main source of data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a reminder, the records of the Swiss parliament are documented in three different types of documents (see our blogpost on this &lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_3-datasources/">here&lt;/a>).
While the summary documents contain an overview over all discussed bills (described in detail &lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_4-summarydocs_part1/">here (Part 1)&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_5-summarydocs_part2/">here (Part 2)&lt;/a>), the &lt;em>Amtliches Bulletin&lt;/em> is our main source for parliamentary speeches and votes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Summary Documents and the Secrets they Hold -- Part 2</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_5-summarydocs_part2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_5-summarydocs_part2/</guid><description>&lt;p>Summary documents are one of our main sources for the Project &lt;em>130 Years of Swiss Parliament&lt;/em>. As highlighted in &lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_4-summarydocs_part1/">Part 1 of our series on Summary Documents&lt;/a>, we extract a lot of information from these documents.
Most importantly, these documents are our baseline for the complete list of bills presented to parliament. They also include information about cosponsorship signatures, which can be used to study legislative collaborations and alliances.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this blogpost we talk about the numbering of bills as well as presenting some exceptions that caused us some headaches when exporting and structuring their information.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Summary Documents and the Secrets they Hold -- Part 1</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_4-summarydocs_part1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_4-summarydocs_part1/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of our main data sources for our Project &lt;em>130 Years of Swiss Parliament&lt;/em> (&lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/projects/130-years-of-swiss-parliament/">click here for the project overview&lt;/a>) are so-called summary of proceedings documents. The Amtliches Bulltin publishes summary documents (dt. &lt;em>Übersicht der Verhandlungen&lt;/em> or summary of proceedings) for each parliamentary session. These documents contain a list of proposed bills by the members of parliament along with additional information (date of submission, bill text, committee assignments, co-sponsorship, and dates of important decisions).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A new data source: Records of the Swiss Parliament</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_3-datasources/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_3-datasources/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our DemocraSci project builds on three data sources.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>The &lt;code>Amtliches Bulletin&lt;/code>, containing word protocols/proceedings from both chambers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Summary of Proceedings&lt;/code>, containing an overview over all discussed/submitted bills (dt. Geschäfte)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>Additional Protocols&lt;/code>, containing additional word protocols from sessions recorded between 1921 and 1970.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="data.png" alt="Our three main data sources for the project with approximate document count.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The documentation of the Swiss parliamentary sessions are recorded in the &lt;code>Amtliches Bulletin&lt;/code>.
These documentations of the sessions have undergone three mayor changes since the foundation of the Swiss Federal Assembly in 1848.
In 1891, the &lt;code>Amtlichen stenographischen Bulletins&lt;/code> (only in 1963 did the name change to &lt;code>Amtliches Bulletin&lt;/code> due to the staffing change and collaborations between shorthand writers (stenographers) and editors [1, page 27]) was founded to report plenary discussions in from the Swiss Federal Assembly.
Especially for discussions surrounding bills or interventions that are subject to the referendum right, it was considered important to be open about the parliamentary discussions to inform the interested public (as documented in [1, page 11]).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Co-Sponsorship Networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_2-snf-project/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_2-snf-project/</guid><description>&lt;p>Starting in 2019, we were granted an SNF-research project to study how members of the Swiss parliament shaped the Swiss political landscape.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Project details&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>funding agency: Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>duration: 36 months (2019-2022)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Project summary&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Analyses of legislative behavior is often based on ideological positions (or policy preferences) of the involved actors, such as parties or individual members of parliament (MPs). These positions allow for detailed analysis on how political alliances are formed and leveraged to influence the decision-making process in their favour. Over the years the discipline has generated and adapted different methods and measures to estimate ideological positions of political actors. These measures are based on a variety of data sources, such as roll-call voting behavior in parliament, surveys, social media behavior or campaign contributions of MPs. Most of these measures have constraints, either methodologically or based on data availability. Roll-call votes are only informative if this form of voting is standard in a parliament; surveys only report snapshots of positions and are often not answered by all MPs; social media behavior depends on the availability of profiles; and campaign contributions have to be public record.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>SDSC Project: DemocraSci</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_1-sdsc-project/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/news/swissparliament_1-sdsc-project/</guid><description>&lt;p>The goal of our research and data project DemocraSci is to create a searchable database of the Swiss Parliament. For the past 130 years (starting in 1891), the Swiss Parliament has carefully documented its actions and debates in the so-called Amtliches Bulletin&amp;mdash;a stenographic record of parliamentary speeches and legislative proposals. In our project we carefully extract and structure the data from the Amtliches Bulletin.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our database will contain&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>all bills, legislative proposals and parliamentary questions brought forth by members of the parliament, comittees, parliamentary groups (called Fraktionen) and cantons (in the form of a Standesinitative)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>all speeches recorded in the Amtliches Bulletin&lt;/li>
&lt;li>all members passing through the parliament as well as their functions, their committee memberships and their involvement in parliamentary affairs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>all votes and voting outcomes for proposals&lt;/li>
&lt;li>all cosponsorship signatures from members of parliament on bills&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The project is a collaboration between our chair and the &lt;a href="https://datascience.ch">Swiss Data Science Center, SDSC&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>