<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Exploring the hidden knowledge space: Ideas, patents, people on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/</link><description>Recent content in Exploring the hidden knowledge space: Ideas, patents, people on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/cbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/cbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Complex Systems through the Lens of Data-Driven Models: Insights into Social Organizations, Collaborative Innovation, and Supply Chains</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/vaccario/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/vaccario/</guid><description>Abstract In this talk, I will demonstrate how data-driven modeling can explain deviations between observations and expectations in complex systems. Specifically, I will discuss how simple pairwise interactions in social organizations can reveal structural imbalances and why perfectly balanced states are rarely observed. Next, I will examine how collaborations among groups of scientists and firms can either support or hinder innovation and present a unified modeling approach that can capture the various features of these systems.</description></item><item><title>Exploring the adjacent possible: play, anticipation, surprise</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/loreto/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/loreto/</guid><description>Abstract Novelties frequently occur in our individual daily lives. We meet new people, learn and use new words, listen to new songs, watch a new movie, and adopt new technology. Such unique experiences sometimes happen by chance. Often they are triggered by earlier new experiences, thus providing a compelling correlation between their appearances. Historically the notion of the &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; has always offered challenges to humankind. What is new often defies the natural tendency of humans to predict and control future events.</description></item><item><title>Opening</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/schweitzer_opening/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/schweitzer_opening/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Opening</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/schweitzer_opening/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/schweitzer_opening/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Understanding Mobility Patterns through Patents, Publications, and Temporal Network Causal Inference</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/verginer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/verginer/</guid><description>Abstract In this talk, we will explore how patents and scientific publications can be used to infer mobility patterns through network and causal inference methods. By analyzing this information through a network lens, we can uncover patterns of knowledge diffusion and the flow of people and ideas across different fields and regions. Additionally, our novel path analysis tools can identify temporal correlations between mobility patterns and other relevant factors, such as innovation outcomes.</description></item></channel></rss>