<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Exploring the hidden knowledge space: Ideas, patents, people on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/</link><description>Recent content in Exploring the hidden knowledge space: Ideas, patents, people on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/cbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/cbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Complex Systems through the Lens of Data-Driven Models: Insights into Social Organizations, Collaborative Innovation, and Supply Chains</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/vaccario/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/vaccario/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In this talk, I will demonstrate how data-driven modeling can explain deviations between observations and expectations in complex systems.
Specifically, I will discuss how simple pairwise interactions in social organizations can reveal structural imbalances and why perfectly balanced states are rarely observed.
Next, I will examine how collaborations among groups of scientists and firms can either support or hinder innovation and present a unified modeling approach that can capture the various features of these systems.
Finally, I will delve into supply chains and explore their structures and deviations from theoretical expectations.
Throughout the talk, I will emphasize the importance of data and a bottom-up approach in comprehending complex systems and providing unique insights.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Exploring the adjacent possible: play, anticipation, surprise</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/loreto/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/loreto/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Novelties frequently occur in our individual daily lives. We meet new people, learn and use new words, listen to new songs, watch a new movie, and adopt new technology. Such unique experiences sometimes happen by chance. Often they are triggered by earlier new experiences, thus providing a compelling correlation between their appearances. Historically the notion of the &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; has always offered challenges to humankind. What is new often defies the natural tendency of humans to predict and control future events. Still, we base most of our decisions on our expectations about the future. From this perspective, a deep understanding of the underlying mechanisms through which novelties emerge and humans anticipate their occurrence is key to progress in all sectors of human activities. The common intuition that one new thing often leads to another is captured, mathematically, by the notion of &amp;ldquo;adjacent possible&amp;rdquo;, i.e., the set of all those things (ideas, linguistic structures, concepts, molecules, genomes, technological artefacts, etc.) that are one step away from what actually exists. It hence can arise from incremental modifications and recombination of existing material. In this talk, I&amp;rsquo;ll present a mathematical framework describing the expansion of the adjacent possible, whose predictions are borne out in several data sets drawn from social and technological systems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Opening</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/schweitzer_opening/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/schweitzer_opening/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Opening</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/schweitzer_opening/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_sose-december/schweitzer_opening/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Understanding Mobility Patterns through Patents, Publications, and Temporal Network Causal Inference</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/verginer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_april_symp/verginer/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In this talk, we will explore how patents and scientific publications can be used to infer mobility patterns through network and causal inference methods. By analyzing this information through a network lens, we can uncover patterns of knowledge diffusion and the flow of people and ideas across different fields and regions. Additionally, our novel path analysis tools can identify temporal correlations between mobility patterns and other relevant factors, such as innovation outcomes. Our approach is useful not only for understanding mobility patterns in the context of technology transfer and regional development but also for other fields dealing with temporal network data. This research sheds light on the mechanisms that shape knowledge flows and can inform evidence-based policymaking.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>