<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Signed Relations and Structural Balance in Complex Systems: From Data to Models on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/workshop-structural-balance-may-2024/</link><description>Recent content in Signed Relations and Structural Balance in Complex Systems: From Data to Models on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/workshop-structural-balance-may-2024/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>1</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session01/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session01/</guid><description/></item><item><title>2</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session02/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session02/</guid><description/></item><item><title>3</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session03/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session03/</guid><description/></item><item><title>4</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session04/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session04/</guid><description/></item><item><title>5</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session05/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session05/</guid><description/></item><item><title>6</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session06/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session06/</guid><description/></item><item><title>7</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session07/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session07/</guid><description/></item><item><title>8</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session08/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session08/</guid><description/></item><item><title>9</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session09/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/session09/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_2/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_3/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_4/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/cbreak_5/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Analyzing Signed Networks: Insights from Multiscale Structural Balance Theory and Dynamics in High School Social Relations</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/teixeira/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/teixeira/</guid><description>Abstract This presentation delves into the rich landscape of signed networks, approaching the intricate positive and negative relationships that shape social dynamics, including phenomena like polarization and evolving social ties. Offering a dual perspective on theory and dynamics, the first part of the talk will focus on the theoretical complexities of polarization, introducing the &amp;ldquo;Multiscale Semiwalk Balance&amp;rdquo; approach. This methodology addresses computational challenges, providing scalable insights into balance degrees within real-world social systems.</description></item><item><title>Assessing frustration in real-world signed networks: towards a statistical theory of balance</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/gallo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/gallo/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract The abundance of data about social and economic relationships has opened an era in which social theories can be tested against empirical evidence, allowing human behaviour to be analysed like other natural phenomena. Here we focus on balance theory [1], which postulates coherence between positive and negative interactions in real, social networks. To make balance theory testable, one needs 1) a proper representation of social networks, 2) a definition of &amp;ldquo;frustration&amp;rdquo; (or imbalance) and 3) a set of null models to quantify the statistical significance of the latter.</description></item><item><title>Binary Models for Opinion Dynamics and Interpersonal Relationships via Influence and Homophily Mechanisms</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/pasquale/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/pasquale/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract In this talk we propose two discrete time binary models for opinion dynamics. The first one is based on the homophily mechanism. We show that the binary homophily model can drive an initially structurally unbalanced network towards a socially balanced one. In order to characterise non-structurally balanced equilibrium points, we introduce a (V,Σ)-factorization that finds an interesting interpretation in terms of structurally balanced sub-classes.
The second one is a revisitation of a recently proposed discrete time model for the interplay between homophily-based appraisal dynamics and influence-based opinion dynamics.</description></item><item><title>Closing and Farewell</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/holyst/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/holyst/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Collective decision-making on networked systems: From social networks to political decision-making</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/fontan/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/fontan/</guid><description>Abstract Collective decision-making refers to a process in which the agents of a community exchange opinions to reach a common decision. It is often assumed that a collective decision is reached through collaboration among individuals. However, in many contexts, concerning for instance collective human behavior, it is more realistic to assume that the agents can collaborate or compete with each other. In this case, different types of collective behavior can be observed.</description></item><item><title>Conference Dinner -- Restaurant Linde, Universitätstrasse 91</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/confbreak/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/confbreak/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Critical properties of Heider balance on multiplex networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/mohandas/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/mohandas/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract Heider&amp;rsquo;s structural balance theory has proven invaluable in comprehending the dynamics of social groups characterized by both friendly and hostile relationships. Since people&amp;rsquo;s relations are rarely single-faceted, we investigate Heider balance dynamics on a multiplex network, consisting of several copies of the same agent displaying correlated relations at different layers building the multiplex. Intralayer interactions in our model adhere to Heider dynamics, while interlayer correlations stem from Ising interactions, with the heat bath dynamics of link signs.</description></item><item><title>Introduction of Participants</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/introduction/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Keynote: How diadic homophilic relations cause structural balance</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/thurner/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/thurner/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PPTX) Abstract We present a simple model of a society where individuals are represented as a vector of opinions. Individuals are connected to each other in a temporal network where signed links represent a positive or negative relation between them. In a co-evolutionary dynamic setup individuals can change their opinions or change link signs. The model is phrased as a spinglas model. We study the phase diagram of the corresponding Hamiltonian and find that the “triad-statistics” that is expected from structural balance is obtained for specific parameter values.</description></item><item><title>Keynote: Political Polarization At the Age of Social Media</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/szymanski/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/szymanski/</guid><description>Abstract We all agree that social media has changed the way political information spreads across the internet, but there is paucity of research on how exactly this new way of spreading works. In this talk, we will start by discussing the new patterns of data flow and new roles for users in spreading information and this new model coexists with remnants of the classic two-level propagation. Then, using the polarization model inspired by the Ising model, we discuss how the presence of social media increases polarization.</description></item><item><title>Keynote: Structural analysis of signed networks by optimally clustering them using integer programming models</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/aref/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/aref/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract A signed network is one with positive and negative edges. We analyze signed networks from the perspective of balance theory. A signed network is strongly balanced (weakly balanced) if its nodes can be partitioned into k≤2 clusters (k clusters) such that positive edges are within the clusters and negative edges are between the clusters. We use mathematical programming models to optimally cluster the nodes of a network by minimizing the total number of intra-cluster negative and inter-cluster positive edges.</description></item><item><title>Keynote: The Shallowness of Deep Division</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/macy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/macy/</guid><description>Abstract Computational models reveal a tipping point in political polarization beyond which there is a potentially irreversible phase transition characterized by asymmetric hysteresis trajectories and triadic balance.The cascade dynamics display two disturbing properties: opinions become aligned across seemingly disparate political and cultural dimensions, and existential threats to shared interests (like a lethal pandemic, catastrophic global warming, or aggression by a foreign adversary) have a divisive rather than unifying effect.
This unraveling of the social fabric suggests partisan divisions that are deeply rooted in opposing interests and ideologies.</description></item><item><title>Lunch Break</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/lbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/lbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Lunch Break</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/lbreak_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/lbreak_2/</guid><description/></item><item><title>On the Individual Roots of Polarization: Combining Experiments and Modeling</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/sobkowicz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/sobkowicz/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PPTX) Abstract Most of the sociophysical and Agent Based models of opinion dynamics attempting to describe polarization focus on social interactions. The internal mechanisms of the individual opinion changes are usually significantly simplified. One of the reasons for such simplification is that the actual mechanisms are not very well understood in social psychology. They depend heavily on the contexts, the individual mental and emotional state, communication media and multiple, often conflicting forces.</description></item><item><title>Reconstructing signed relations from interaction data</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/andres/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/andres/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract Positive and negative relations play an essential role in human behaviour and shape our communities. Polarization in the internal structure of these communities strongly affects their functioning. Imagine a community where two groups of individuals have positive relations within but negative relations across the groups. While such a polarized setting is stable according to structural balance theory, it may hinder constructive dialogue, foster division, and impede collective problem-solving.</description></item><item><title>Stable Signed Networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/buechel/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/buechel/</guid><description>Abstract While standard social networks suppress negative ties, signed networks capture them by coding relations as +1 if positive, −1 if negative, and 0 if neutral. The economics literature on social networks has always had a particular focus on strategic network formation, but signed networks have been largely ignored. Hence, there is the fundamental question: How do signed networks form among strategic agents? We address this question by studying how agents strategically form and dissolve positive and negative ties.</description></item><item><title>Structural balance in complex network: Observation, Emergence and Implications</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/vaccario/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/vaccario/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Since its first conceptualization in psychology, the theory of Structural balance was extended to economics, ecology and social science. Trespassing disciplinary boundaries, one of its first simple network formulations posits that triangles in signed networks should have an even number of negative links. This very simple statement has two significant consequences. First, it strongly affects our expectations about the macroscopic structure and functioning of an analyzed system. Second, it allows us to define specific dynamics at the microscopic level, i.</description></item><item><title>The fragility of opinion formation in a complex world</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/medo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/medo/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract How does the complexity of the world around us affect the reliability of our opinions? Motivated by this question, we discuss a simple model in which an observer gradually forms opinions about a world composed of subjects interconnected by a signed network of mutual trust and distrust.
We show that when the underlying signed network is not balanced, the opinion formation process is highly fragile. An individual who initially trusts a few credible information sources, for example, likely ends up trusting many deceptive information sources.</description></item><item><title>Under-representation of nonhierarchical triads in structural balance model</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/gorski/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/gorski/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract We introduce an agent-based model integrating structural balance and status, which are prominent theories of signed link formation process. For complete networks, our analytics matches simulations showing continuous or discontinuous phase transition between unbalanced and structurally balanced paradise states. We identify nonhierarchical triads for which principles of status theory are broken.
Extending our analysis to large online and small face-to-face networks, we observe that nonhierarchical triads tend to be under-represented.</description></item><item><title>Unpacking Polarization: Antagonism and Alignment in Signed Networks of Online Interaction</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/fraxanet/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/fraxanet/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract Political conflict is an essential element of democratic systems, but can also threaten their existence if it becomes too intense. This happens particularly when most polit- ical issues become aligned along the same major fault line, splitting society into two antagonistic camps. In the 20th century, major fault lines were formed by structural conflicts, like owners vs workers, center vs periphery, etc. But these classical cleav- ages have since lost their explanatory power.</description></item><item><title>Welcome and Introductory Remarks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/schweitzer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2024_workshop_may/schweitzer/</guid><description>Presentation Slides
(PgUp, PgDown to navigate, TAB for overview)
Research project Signed Relations and Structural Balance in Complex Systems: From Data to Models (SNSF grant 192746)</description></item></channel></rss>