<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Events on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/</link><description>Recent content in Events on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Social Software Engineering</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-december-2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-december-2023/</guid><description>Software development still depends on humans. The foundation of any successful software project lies in the expertise, skills, and creativity of the individuals involved. As technology continues to evolve towards artificial intelligence, it is essential to recognize the profound impact of human capital — ranging from technical proficiency and educational background to the sheer passion that drives innovation.
But there is more to it. Software development today is predominantly social software engineering.</description></item><item><title>Signed Relations and Structural Balance in Complex Systems: From Data to Models</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/workshop-structural-balance-may-2024/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/workshop-structural-balance-may-2024/</guid><description>Venue Wednesday 17 May, Friday 19 May ETH Zurich, Lecture Hall E101 LEE Building, Tannenstrasse 3, 8006 Zürich Link to map
Thursday 18 May ETH Zurich, GAP Lecture Hall ML E12 ML Building, Tannenstrasse 3, 8006 Zürich Link to map
Synopsis According to the theory of structural balance, interacting systems balance the (positive or negative) relations between different system elements such that local conflicts are minimized. Hence, structural imbalances induce a dynamics to resolve such conflicts.</description></item><item><title>Exploring the hidden knowledge space: Ideas, patents, people</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/</guid><description>Hidden knowledge is the &amp;ldquo;known unknown&amp;rdquo;. We know it is out there, but we don’t know yet what it is. So, how could we search for it? And what should we expect to find? These questions are explored in three different talks.
Vittorio Loreto focuses on the novelties that are just around the corner. The &amp;ldquo;adjacent possible&amp;rdquo; can be detected because one new thing leads to another. Giacomo Vaccario challenges our knowledge about complex systems, pointing out the mismatch between our theoretical expectations and reality.</description></item><item><title>Datenanalyse für die Digital Humanities: Projekte, Methoden, Einsichten</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/digital-humanities/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/digital-humanities/</guid><description>Veranstaltungsort Raum 02.002, Zentrales Hörsaalgebäude Z6 am Campus Hubland
Hubland Süd, 97074 Würzburg Link zur Karte
Synopsis Der Workshop bringt 20 Wissenschaftlerinnen und Wissenschaftler aus den Sozial- und Geisteswissenschaften (Geschichte, Theologie, Literatur, Kultur) und den Computer- und Komplexitätswissenschaften (Datenanalyse, maschinelles Lernen, Netzwerkanalyse) zusammen, um die Herausforderungen für die &amp;ldquo;Digital Humanities&amp;rdquo; zu diskutieren.
Drei unterschiedliche Perspektiven werden thematisiert: &amp;ldquo;Projekte&amp;rdquo; geben einen Überblick über verfügbare Daten, ausgewählte Korpora, die teilweise digitalisiert, transkribiert und klassifiziert wurden (Briefkorrespondenzen, aber auch Sammlungen von Artefakten), &amp;ldquo;Methoden&amp;rdquo; zeigen auf, wie solche Korpora mit Hilfe von Netzwerkwerkzeugen analysiert werden können,</description></item><item><title>Measuring, Modeling and Mitigating Opinion Polarization and Political Cleavage (MMM)</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/mmm-workshop-september-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/mmm-workshop-september-2023/</guid><description>Venue ETH Zurich, Lecture Hall ML E12 ML Building, Tannenstrasse 3, 8006 Zürich Link to map
Synopsis Political polarization and radicalization is more and more seen as a major threat for democratic countries, with alarming consequences. Therefore, research on this topic has vastly increased in different scientific disciplines. But the scientific discourse lacks an integrative perspective on polarization, merging methods and insights from different disciplines. Even more, we miss the exchange between formal modelers, political scientists and sociologists which only would allow to develop such a common perspective.</description></item><item><title>The Complex Network Approach to Data Science</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/</guid><description>This SG Symposium will take place at ETH Zürich in Room LEE E 101 on November 24, 2022 from 09:00 to 12:00.
We bring together researchers working on complex networks and data science. We would like to create a platform for exchanging ideas, results, and new methodologies, and to develop new concepts for data-driven research. A coffee break will precede the last talk.
How to find LEE E 101.</description></item></channel></rss>