<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Events on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/</link><description>Recent content in Events on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Complexity of Social and Economic Systems: From Models to Measures</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-final-symposium-october-2024/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 11:01:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-final-symposium-october-2024/</guid><description>&lt;!-- ![group_pic.jpeg](group_pic.jpeg) -->
&lt;h2 id="venue">Venue&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>ETH Zurich Main Building, Audi Max F30 &lt;br>
Rämistrasse 101, 8092 Zürich&lt;/br>
&lt;a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/cNFRoJCtQpPJrCpa8">Link to map&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;a href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/final-workshop-form/" style="display: inline-block; padding: 8px 16px; font-size: 16px; font-weight: bold; color: white; background-color: #581616; border-radius: 5px; text-decoration: none; transition: transform 0.2s;">
 Register Here
&lt;/a>
&lt;style>
a:hover {
 transform: translateY(-3px);
}
&lt;/style>
&lt;h2 id="synopsis">Synopsis&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In October 2004, Frank Schweitzer established the Chair of Systems Design at ETH Zürich. This symposium celebrates the 20th anniversary of the Chair and also marks the final one under his leadership. Each of the three sessions exemplifies, pars pro toto, the success of the Chair’s interdisciplinary approach.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Social Software Engineering</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-december-2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-december-2023/</guid><description>&lt;p>Software development still depends on humans. The foundation of any successful software project lies in the expertise, skills, and creativity of the individuals involved. As technology continues to evolve towards artificial intelligence, it is essential to recognize the profound impact of human capital — ranging from technical proficiency and educational background to the sheer passion that drives innovation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But there is more to it. Software development today is predominantly social software engineering. Collaboration relies on cooperation, communication and coordination in developer teams. In this Symposium, we will explore the role of social capital in software development.
Specifically, the speakers will discuss how to enhance communication and leadership, and facilitate collective problem-solving.
The talks will provide insights into the shift from solo to collaborative development practices, how code review affects team dynamics, and what we can learn from the developer networks of open-source projects.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Signed Relations and Structural Balance in Complex Systems: From Data to Models</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/workshop-structural-balance-may-2024/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/workshop-structural-balance-may-2024/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="group_pic.jpeg" alt="group_pic.jpeg">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="venue">Venue&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Wednesday 15 May 2024, Friday 17 May 2024&lt;/strong> &lt;br>
ETH Zurich, Lecture Hall E101 &lt;br>
LEE Building, Leonhardstr 21, 8092 Zürich&lt;/br>
&lt;a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/RSMt8v2HxA6x8u9y7">Link to map&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Thursday 16 May 2024&lt;/strong> &lt;br>
ETH Zurich, Alumni Pavillon MM C78.1 &lt;br>
Polyterrasse, 8001 Zürich&lt;/br>
&lt;a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/aAJoQiEjWewFy1DFA">Link to map&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="synopsis">Synopsis&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>According to the theory of structural balance, interacting systems balance the (positive or negative) relations between different system elements such that local conflicts are minimized. Hence, structural imbalances induce a dynamics to resolve such conflicts. This dynamics plays a vital role in evolutionary processes because a multitude of possible solutions exists. At the same time, if these solutions cannot be reached, this can hamper the functionality of systems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Exploring the hidden knowledge space: Ideas, patents, people</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hidden knowledge is the &amp;ldquo;known unknown&amp;rdquo;.
We know it is out there, but we don’t know yet what it is.
So, how could we search for it? And what should we expect to find?
These questions are explored in three different talks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vittorio Loreto focuses on the novelties that are just around the corner.
The &amp;ldquo;adjacent possible&amp;rdquo; can be detected because one new thing leads to another.
Giacomo Vaccario challenges our knowledge about complex systems, pointing out the mismatch between our theoretical expectations and reality.
Luca Verginer uncovers patterns in knowledge diffusion and mobility, to enhance evidence-based policymaking.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Datenanalyse für die Digital Humanities: Projekte, Methoden, Einsichten</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/digital-humanities/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/digital-humanities/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="veranstaltungsort">Veranstaltungsort&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Raum 02.002, &lt;br>
Zentrales Hörsaalgebäude Z6 am Campus Hubland&lt;br>
Hubland Süd, 97074 Würzburg&lt;/br>
&lt;a href="https://goo.gl/maps/sJmo2qQCf7Hbkq8r9">Link zur Karte&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="synopsis">Synopsis&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Der Workshop bringt 20 Wissenschaftlerinnen und Wissenschaftler aus den Sozial- und Geisteswissenschaften (Geschichte, Theologie, Literatur, Kultur) und den Computer- und Komplexitätswissenschaften (Datenanalyse, maschinelles Lernen, Netzwerkanalyse) zusammen, um die Herausforderungen für die &amp;ldquo;Digital Humanities&amp;rdquo; zu diskutieren.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Drei unterschiedliche Perspektiven werden thematisiert: &lt;br>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Projekte&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> geben einen Überblick über verfügbare &lt;strong>Daten&lt;/strong>, ausgewählte Korpora, die teilweise digitalisiert, transkribiert und klassifiziert wurden (Briefkorrespondenzen, aber auch Sammlungen von Artefakten), &lt;br>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Methoden&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> zeigen auf, wie solche Korpora mit Hilfe von Netzwerkwerkzeugen &lt;strong>analysiert&lt;/strong> werden können,&lt;br>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Einblicke&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> illustrieren anhand von Beispielen, wie &lt;strong>Wissen&lt;/strong> durch die Anwendung digitaler Methoden generiert wurde, zeigen aber auch die Probleme und Gefahren bei der &lt;strong>Interpretation&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Die Forschung der &amp;ldquo;Digital Humanities&amp;rdquo; ist zu oft in disziplinären Aktivitäten isoliert. Der Workshop soll einen neuen Diskurs ermöglichen, der über die Grenzen wissenschaftlicher Disziplinen hinaus reicht.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Measuring, Modeling and Mitigating Opinion Polarization and Political Cleavage (MMM)</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/mmm-workshop-september-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/mmm-workshop-september-2023/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="venue">Venue&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>ETH Zurich, Lecture Hall ML E12 &lt;br>
ML Building, Tannenstrasse 3, 8006 Zürich&lt;/br>
&lt;a href="https://goo.gl/maps/edTXsXWgfXT5MzqZ7">Link to map&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="synopsis">Synopsis&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Political polarization and radicalization is more and more seen as a major threat for democratic countries, with alarming consequences. Therefore, research on this topic has vastly increased in different scientific disciplines. But the scientific discourse lacks an integrative perspective on polarization, merging methods and insights from different disciplines. Even more, we miss the exchange between formal modelers, political scientists and sociologists which only would allow to develop such a common perspective. Our workshop shall fill this gap, bringing together an interdisciplinary group of top scientists, to foster awareness, acceptance, and adoption of insights from the respective disciplines.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Complex Network Approach to Data Science</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/</guid><description>&lt;p>This SG Symposium will take place at ETH Zürich in Room LEE E 101 on November 24, 2022 from 09:00 to 12:00.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We bring together researchers working on complex networks and data science. We would like to create a platform for exchanging ideas, results, and new methodologies, and to develop new concepts for data-driven research.
A coffee break will precede the last talk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://ethz.ch/staffnet/en/service/rooms-and-buildings/orientierung/gebaeude.html?args0=LEE">How to find LEE E 101.&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>