<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Events on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/</link><description>Recent content in Events on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Exploring the hidden knowledge space: Ideas, patents, people</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-april-2023/</guid><description>This symposium delves into the hidden realm of knowledge, ideas, patents, and human interactions, featuring expert presentations by Prof. Vittorio Loreto, Dr. Giacomo Vaccario, and Dr. Luca Verginer. Each presentation will address facets of innovation, collaboration, and mobility. Utilizing data-driven models and innovative methodological approaches, the speakers discuss insights on the complexities of these systems.
How to find the WEV, F111</description></item><item><title>Datenanalyse für die Digital Humanities: Projekte, Methoden, Einsichten</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/digital-humanities/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/digital-humanities/</guid><description>Veranstaltungsort Raum 02.002, Zentrales Hörsaalgebäude Z6 am Campus Hubland
Hubland Süd, 97074 Würzburg Link zur Karte
Synopsis Der Workshop bringt 20 Wissenschaftlerinnen und Wissenschaftler aus den Sozial- und Geisteswissenschaften (Geschichte, Theologie, Literatur, Kultur) und den Computer- und Komplexitätswissenschaften (Datenanalyse, maschinelles Lernen, Netzwerkanalyse) zusammen, um die Herausforderungen für die &amp;ldquo;Digital Humanities&amp;rdquo; zu diskutieren.
Drei unterschiedliche Perspektiven werden thematisiert: &amp;ldquo;Projekte&amp;rdquo; geben einen Überblick über verfügbare Daten, ausgewählte Korpora, die teilweise digitalisiert, transkribiert und klassifiziert wurden (Briefkorrespondenzen, aber auch Sammlungen von Artefakten), &amp;ldquo;Methoden&amp;rdquo; zeigen auf, wie solche Korpora mit Hilfe von Netzwerkwerkzeugen analysiert werden können,</description></item><item><title>The Complex Network Approach to Data Science</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/sg-symposium-november-2022/</guid><description>This SG Symposium will take place at ETH Zürich in Room LEE E 101 on November 24, 2022 from 09:00 to 12:00.
We bring together researchers working on complex networks and data science. We would like to create a platform for exchanging ideas, results, and new methodologies, and to develop new concepts for data-driven research. A coffee break will precede the last talk.
How to find LEE E 101.</description></item></channel></rss>