<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Measuring, Modeling and Mitigating Opinion Polarization and Political Cleavage (MMM) on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/mmm-workshop-september-2023/</link><description>Recent content in Measuring, Modeling and Mitigating Opinion Polarization and Political Cleavage (MMM) on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/events/mmm-workshop-september-2023/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Belief Heterogeneity</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session04/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session04/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Changing Opinions</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session05/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session05/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Co-Evolution of Relations and Opinions</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session08/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session08/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Inferring Opinions and Reconstructing Relations</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session07/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session07/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Measuring Polarization: Moving Beyond Single Dimensions</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session06/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session06/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mechanism Design and Polarization Mitigation Strategies</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session09/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session09/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mechanisms Behind Polarization Dynamics</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session02/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session02/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mitigating (Online) Polarization</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session03/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session03/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Polarization as a Threat to Democracy?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session01/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/session01/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_2/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_3/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_4/</guid><description/></item><item><title>☕️ Coffee Break 🥐</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/cbreak_5/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A Textual Time Capsule: A Text-Based Approach to Tracing Swiss Elite Polarization Across 130 Years</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/schlosser/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/schlosser/</guid><description>Abstract Increased polarization has long been lamented as a sign of democratic instability and erosion. It is a phenomenon constantly postulated to have increased in the past few decades. However, this has yet to be studied over a prolonged period, and Switzerland is no exception. Thus, we ask whether this claim still holds when studying polarization over the past 130 years in the Swiss parliament.
To achieve this, we employ text embeddings to compute multi-dimensional representations of Swiss parliament members based on the legislative bills introduced, from 1891 to today.</description></item><item><title>Algorithmic bias and multidimensional political polarisation in online social networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/iniguez/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/iniguez/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract Political polarization in online social networks is a rapidly growing phenomenon worldwide, happening within a pervasive, variable, and mostly hidden ecosystem of content filtering technologies that determine what information we see online. Despite the relevance of algorithms and opinion formation mechanisms to modern-day political discourse, the structure and dynamics of polarized states in digital spaces are still poorly understood.
In this talk I’ll introduce a general theoretical framework to systematically link models of opinion dynamics, social network structure, and content filtering, allowing us to pinpoint what type of social interactions are robust against algorithmic bias, and which ones are susceptible to bias-enhanced opinion polarization.</description></item><item><title>An Empirical and Simulation Investigation of Bounded Confidence and Negative Influence in Opinion Dynamics using Stochastic Actor-Oriented Model</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/tang/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/tang/</guid><description>Abstract Classic opinion dynamics models of assimilation fail to shed light on opinion clustering and polarization. Two micro-processes of social influence, bounded confidence and negative influence, have been proposed as solutions. Empirical evidence for bounded confidence and negative influence is debatable. Two common drawbacks in existing empirical studies are (1) lab experiments that lack external validity; and (2) model designs that do not allow disentangling negative influence from bounded confidence, as well as other social influence mechanisms.</description></item><item><title>Closing and Farewell</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/closing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/closing/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Democratic backsliding, attitudes towards democracy and affective polarization</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/wunsch/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/wunsch/</guid><description>Abstract Affective polarization and partisanship have been posited as a key explanation for citizens’tolerance towards democratic backsliding, with voters more likely to overlook democratic violations conducted by in-party candidates. Our study adopts a novel perspective on this relationship: focusing on the role of the opposition, we contend that backsliding may crystallize anaffective dislike among opposition supporters towards the governing party and its supporters that stems from a regime divide over democracy itself.</description></item><item><title>Depolarizing effect of strategic anticonformity – insights from the three-state 𝑞-voter model with bounded confidence</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/weron/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/weron/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract Engaging with dissenting views, fostering productive disagreements, or strategic anticonformity can bring benefits to organizations by challenging the status quo. However, a key question arises regarding whether such strategic anticonformity ultimately leads to social polarization, which is an undesirable outcome. Previous research in computational social science indicates that conformity combined with homophily enhances polarization, while anticonformity towards dissimilar individuals further escalates it. However, it is worth noting that anticonformity is not limited to dissimilar individuals and can manifest in various forms, one of which is asserting uniqueness.</description></item><item><title>Do left-wing governments fuel far-right success?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/wagner/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/wagner/</guid><description>Abstract In the last decades support for the far right has surged in countries all over the world. One of the explanations of this success alludes to voters’ reaction to the policies implemented by mainstream parties, although it is unclear which are more likely to fuel their advance. In this paper we investigate the causal effect of the partisanship of the incumbent government on the electoral results of far-right parties. To do that, we use a threefold empirical strategy, combining cross-country over time comparative data, quasi-experimental RDD evidence in the case of Spain, and individual-level survey data to test the mechanisms behind the main effect.</description></item><item><title>Do we need more than one dimension to understand polarization?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/olbrich/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/olbrich/</guid><description>Abstract It seems natural to think about about polarization along an one-dimensional spaces, i.e. along a single axes or between two groups, respectively. In my contribution I will discuss, why this might not be sufficient and how to work in higher dimensional spaces. In particular, I will discuss this problem in the context of cleavage theory and the hypothesis that the populist right parties that appeared in Europe in the last decades are part of a new cleavage.</description></item><item><title>How assimilative and idiosyncratic attitude change generate oscillations of public policy mood</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/lorenz/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/lorenz/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract The ideological attitudes of the general public in the US show two characteristics in their temporal evolution. When measured by self-identification, the distribution stays almost constant with a large moderate peak and a tendency for smaller and blurred liberal and conservative peaks. When conceptualized and measured as public policy mood instead, they oscillate almost regularly. We reproduce both phenomena in an agent-based model. In the model, agents repeatedly adjust their position either idiosyncratically but more often through assimilative attitude change towards the positions of others whenever these positions are within a latitude of acceptance.</description></item><item><title>Introduction of Participants</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/introduction/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Lunch Break</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_dh/lbreak_1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_dh/lbreak_1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Lunch Break</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/lbreak_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/lbreak_2/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Multidimensional party polarization in Europe: Cross-cutting divides and effective dimensionality</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/steenbergen/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/steenbergen/</guid><description>Abstract Ideological polarization matters. It is a necessary requirement for meaningful electoral competition, but at its extreme can strain democratic functioning. The conceptualization and measurement of contemporary ideological polarization is complicated by the growing complexity of the policy differences between political parties. Yet, existing indicators remain one-dimensional in nature, despite the wide acceptance of the multidimensional structure of European politics.
To resolve this tension, we introduce a novel, two-dimensional measure of party polarization.</description></item><item><title>On the design of public debate in social networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/grabisch/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/grabisch/</guid><description>Abstract We propose a model of the joint evolution of opinions and social relationshipsin a setting where social influence decays over time. The dynamics are based on bounded confidence: social connections between individuals with distant opinionsare severed while new connections are formed between individuals with similar opinions. Our model naturally gives raise to strong diversity, i.e., the persistenceof heterogeneous opinions in connected societies, a phenomenon that most existingmodels fail to capture.</description></item><item><title>Polarisation in the bounded confidence model: A revised view</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/hegselmann/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/hegselmann/</guid><description>Abstract The bounded confidence model (BC model) is a very simple model: Period by period, all agents average over all opinions that are no further away from their actual opinion than a given distance epsilon, their &amp;lsquo;bounded confidence&amp;rsquo;. It was introduced by Hegselmann and Krause in [2002].
According to the analysis at that time, it appeared that BC processes monotonically lead to a decreasing number of final clusters as the confidence interval (given by epsilon) increases.</description></item><item><title>Polarization Metrics and Opinions Inference in Multipolar Systems</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/benito/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/benito/</guid><description>Abstract Based on the idea that a population is perfectly polarized when divided in two groups of the same size and contrasting opinions, we propose a general methodology to study and measure the emergence of polarization from social interactions.
We will present polarization metrics to opinion distributions. In particular, we propose the polarization index [1] for bipolar systems. This metric is very restrictive since the maximum value is only achieved when the two conditions (groups of the same size and with contrasting opinions), are fulfilled.</description></item><item><title>Political polarization: Persistent hatred or issue-dependent sidings?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/faqeeh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/faqeeh/</guid><description>Abstract In our recent work, we designed two approaches to investigate polarization patterns in political and social platforms. These approaches offer two measures, rigidity and alignment, to quantify the intensity of consistency in polarization patterns from two different aspects; this is used to demonstrate to what extent the polarization in opinions might be independent of ideology and basically the issue or the policy domain at hand, and instead it is derived by fixated antagonism or partisanship.</description></item><item><title>Reconstructing signed relations from interaction data</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/andres/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/andres/</guid><description>Abstract Positive and negative relations play an essential role in human behaviour and shape our communities. Polarization in the internal structure of these communities strongly affects their functioning. Imagine a community where two groups of individuals have positive relations within but negative relations across the groups. While such a polarized setting is stable according to structural balance theory, it may hinder constructive dialogue, foster division, and impede collective problem-solving.
To understand if a community is polarized in its relational structure, it is imperative to possess data on the signs of the relations.</description></item><item><title>Tracing the Sources of Belief Contestation in Policy Debates</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/leifeld/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/leifeld/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract Political actors agree or disagree with other actors on policy beliefs. When aggregated into a policy subsystem, advocacy coalitions with distinct belief systems emerge from actors&amp;rsquo; individual policy belief portfolios. Discourse network analysis measures coalitions by considering actors&amp;rsquo; stated beliefs. But policy beliefs differ in how important they are in structuring coalitions. To understand the ideational &amp;ldquo;glue&amp;rdquo; that binds coalitions together or keeps them apart in any given subsystem, we must identify the joint subset of beliefs that is structurally most important for the coalition structure.</description></item><item><title>Unpacking polarization: Antagonism and Alignment in Signed Networks of Online Interaction</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/garcia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/garcia/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (Online) Abstract Online polarization research currently focuses on studying single-issue opinion distributions or computing distance metrics of interaction network structures. Limited data availability often restricts studies to positive interaction data, which can misrepresent the reality of a discussion. We introduce a novel framework that aims at combining these three aspects, content and interactions, as well as their nature (positive or negative), while challenging the prevailing notion of polarization as an umbrella term for all forms of online conflict or opposing opinions.</description></item><item><title>Welcome and Introductory Remarks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/schweitzer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/schweitzer/</guid><description>Presentation Slides (PDF) Abstract Polarization is studied in different disciplines. For the workshop, we aim at combining research on that topic from computational social science and political science, sociophysics and complexity science.
Each of these disciplines provides a unique perspective: Social and political scientists discuss the reasons and consequences for increasing polarization on various levels of society. Political scientists, in particular, study how this dynamics manifests itself in parliamentary processes, with the US Congress as a prime example.</description></item><item><title>When contact backfires, and when it does not. A social influence model of the dynamics of affective polarization</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/flache/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/flache/</guid><description>Abstract Concerns about increasing affective polarization have renewed interest in interpersonal intergroup contact as a possible remedy against mutually negative outgroup attitudes in society. Recent research increasingly recognizes that individual intergroup contact is but one element in a larger set of interacting processes that occur in interpersonal social interactions both within and between groups.
Advancing earlier work (Flache, 2018), we present a computational agent-based model of the dynamics of intergroup attitudes that encompasses interpersonal intergroup contact as one element, but adds that attitudes towards groups are also socially influenced by ingroup-peers, that the interpersonal relations through which contact and social influence occur are themselves subject to network changes, and that attitudes towards the own and other groups are interconnected.</description></item><item><title>Why can’t we go back to paradise?</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/holyst/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/talks/2023_mmm/holyst/</guid><description>Abstract According to the structural balance theory a social network is in an equilibrium state when it is divided into two communities and there are friendly links inside communities and hostile links between them. Then rules “friend of my friend is my friend” and “enemy of my friend is my enemy” etc are fulfilled. Such a configuration corresponds to the social polarization and can be a result (for example) of segregating ideologies or opposing interests existing in both communities.</description></item></channel></rss>