<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Courses on Chair of Systems Design</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/</link><description>Recent content in Courses on Chair of Systems Design</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 09:36:03 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Master, Bachelor and Semester Theses</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/theses-msc/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/theses-msc/</guid><description>We offer Semester, Bachelor, Master and MAS Theses to ETH Students from the following Departments: D-MTEC, D-PHYS, D-MAVT, and D-MATH.
To qualify for a Master theses, D-MTEC students are require to have taken the following courses:
Systems Dynamics and Complexity, Agent-Based Modelling of Social Systems, Complex Networks. All students are required to sign the declaration of originality.
List of Theses 2022 Vincent Jung (Master Thesis): &amp;ldquo;Ideological Embeddings of Swiss Members of Parliament&amp;rdquo;</description></item><item><title>New: Data Science for Social Challenges</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/data-science-for-social-challenges/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 09:36:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/data-science-for-social-challenges/</guid><description>Many of today&amp;rsquo;s societal challenges cannot be adequately grasped simply by observing human behavior. To make these challenges visible and address their causes, we have to make use of advanced statistics in order to disentangle complex interdependencies between the driving factors.
In this course, we use methods of statistical inference to measure, analyze and interpret social behavior. The course aims at building up methodological skills and places a strong focus on interpretation and reflection of results.</description></item><item><title>Social Data Science</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/social-data-science/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 13:58:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/social-data-science/</guid><description>Description Social Data Science is an emerging field that studies human behavior and social interaction through digital traces. The revolution in measurement brought by our digital society gives us data at global scales, very high frequencies, and unprecedented levels of depth and resolution.
This course focuses both on the fundamentals and applications of Data Science in the Social Sciences, including technologies for data retrieval, processing, and analysis with the aim to derive insights that are interpretable from a wider theoretical perspective.</description></item><item><title>Systems Dynamics and Complexity</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/system-dynamics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 21:43:22 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/system-dynamics/</guid><description>The course encompasses a large range of approaches towards systems and their dynamics, with particular emphasis on problem solving. It starts from basic insights on why real problems are not simple but complex, and why systems do not always do what we expect.
Based on that, we introduce tools and methods commonly used in Systems Engineering (systems oriented management) and Project Management to analyse problems at large, to search for solutions and to optimize project scheduling.</description></item><item><title>Agent-based Modelling of Social Systems</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/abm/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 21:43:13 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/abm/</guid><description>Individuals live in groups! Their weave of dynamical and differentiated interactions results in complex societies, whose properties and ruling principles can only be fully unraveled when studying the underlying social system from a formal standpoint.
In this course, we use agent-based modelling as a bottom-up tool to study social systems. Agents have internal degrees of freedom (opinions, strategies), the ability to perceive and to change their environment, and to interact with other agents.</description></item><item><title>Complex Networks</title><link>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/complex-networks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 21:36:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.sg.ethz.ch/courses/complex-networks/</guid><description>
The course provides an overview of the methods and abstractions used in:
the quantitative study of complex networks empirical network analysis the study of dynamical processes in networked systems the analysis of systemic risk in networked systems the study of network evolution data mining techniques for networked data sets. Useful Information Lecturer: Prof. Frank Schweitzer Tutorials: Dr. Luca Verginer Course ID: 363-0588-00L Period: Spring Semester Syllabus: PDF Moodle: Moodle Board</description></item></channel></rss>